<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>RL  </title>
<link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/</link>
<atom:link href="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description>Science &amp; society</description>
<image>
<url>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/banner_blog_card.png</url>
<title>RL  </title>
<link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/</link>
</image>
<generator>quarto-1.6.1</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 22:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>OpenAI business model: towards private AGI?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/privateAI/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>An alliance between the whimsical Elon Musk and the austere Bill Gates may come as a surprise. But it has just yielded its first fruit – and not a small one at that. A year after the agreement signed by the companies OpenAI and Microsoft, the “GPT-3” algorithm was officially announced on 28th of May, 2020 in a scientific publication (see here). Although it isn’t yet the super-intelligence transhumanists dream of, the breakthrough is significant enough to elicit real policy issues. Overview.</p>
<section id="the-internet-in-the-blender" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-internet-in-the-blender">The internet in the blender</h3>
<p>The performance of this oversized neural network (175 billion parameters) makes the world’s geeks and techno-skeptics fantasize and shiver at its capacity to imitate human beings in an incredible diversity of linguistic contexts. This includes not only translation, spelling correction, sentence auto-completion, but also answering open questions, writing texts that mimic the style of known authors and coding web pages – and even a surprising ability to solve arithmetic problems (links to applications <a href="https://dev.to/amananandrai/top-10-best-uses-of-gpt-3-175n">here</a> and <a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2020/07/20/1005454/openai-machine-learning-language-generator-gpt-3-nlp/">here</a>).</p>
<p>All this is done without any human supervision whatsoever: the neural network is simply trained to predict the next word within a gigantic linguistic corpus containing several billion sentences. To give an idea of the amount of data involved, the whole of Wikipedia represents a mere 3% of this dataset. Ultimately, it’s a big chunk of the Internet – saved every month by [the non-for-profit organization] <a href="https://commoncrawl.org/">Common Crawl</a> – that goes through the blender, using the computational principle of the “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Transformer_(machine_learning_model)">Transformer</a>” deep learning model for natural language processing developed just three years ago by engineers at Google. In short, this method allows a much deeper contextualization of the meaning of each word by considering the word’s position in the sentence and relying on a so-called “attentional” mechanism that enables the algorithm to relate distant linguistic units in such a way that it can link the subject, the verb and the direct object complement in a long sentence such as “The eight-year-old <strong>boy</strong> <strong>eats</strong> a juicy <strong>apple</strong>”. The algorithm can also take into account the semantic context linking different sentences in the same paragraph.</p>
<p>This text is not meant to be a review of all GPT-3 applications (GPT-3 stands for&nbsp; “Third-Generation Generative Pretrained Transformer”). But we do need to mention the most spectacular one: its success in passing the famous Turing Test – or at least, a particular version of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Turing_test">Turing’s test</a>, as it exists in numerous forms. OpenAI scientists indeed invited more than 600 participants to evaluate whether a series of short journalistic texts had been generated by an artificial intelligence or by a human. The verdict: the texts (generated from a title and a heading) by the most perfected version of the algorithm are indistinguishable (to human observers) from those generated by real-life journalists.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/privateAI/turinggpt3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Evolution of the capacity to detect texts written by the IA from Open IA as a function of the parameters used by the neural network. With 175 billion parameters, (at the far right of the curve), the texts become indistinguishable to human observers. For an example of these texts, see the “Additional reading” section below.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="when-size-matters" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="when-size-matters">When size matters</h3>
<p>Beyond this technical feat, the paper by OpenAI reports a much more significant result for the area’s future. To understand this, we have to consider a debate that’s being ongoing in the scientific community since the advent of “deep learning”. In spite of the impressive performance of these new networks, whose paternity is attributed to researcher <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yann_LeCun">Yann LeCun</a>, head of the AI department at Facebook, many experts think that one or several conceptual breakthroughs will be needed to achieve the state of general artificial intelligence (GAI), that is, to produce an algorithm that substantially surpasses human intelligence. In other words, it will take some time, and many problems will have to be solved, before being able to even outline the path to such technology. This, by the way, has been the opinion of Yann LeCun himself during the numerous public conferences he has given to demystify AI (see <a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/yann_lecun_deep_learning_neural_networks_and_the_future_of_ai">here</a>). But not everybody agrees, and certain points of view are less comforting. Some people think that the problem with GAI is mainly a problem of computing power, that is, a technological problem rather than a conceptual one.</p>
<p>And this is what makes the OpenAI paper interesting. Indeed, it shows that the increase in performance seems to be directly dependent on the increase of computing power, without any obvious sign of saturation. This means that, by constructing a super-computer even more powerful than the one lent by Microsoft to run GPT-3, we could achieve significantly better performance. Note that this strategy poses real <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/robtoews/2020/06/17/deep-learnings-climate-change-problem/#ebfbb2e6b438">problems</a> given the energetic needs of super-computers…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/privateAI/precision_parametres.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="432"></p>
<figcaption><em>Continuous increase in the algorithm’s precision with an increasing number of parameters.</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Therefore, it cannot be excluded that a major breakthrough will be made simply by spending more money and means on the infrastructures (which <a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/ai/openai-azure-supercomputer/">Microsoft is planning to do</a>). If this is the case, it is urgent to reflect collectively on the implications. Today, it is clear that the sector’s dominant actors – Google, Facebook, and OpenAI – are of two minds. On one side, they wish to communicate their progress so as to attract the best scientists and, on the other, they fear eliciting an excessive reaction from public opinion, which could translate into consumer boycotts or a coordinated legal effort at the international scale. The assessment of what it will take to develop a machine even remotely similar to an GAI has an obvious impact on how politicians and the media consider this technology. Right now, no one knows how far we have come, but progress has clearly been huge in every field directly linked to AI, starting with linguistic modeling, statistics, and neuroscience.</p>
<section id="a-partnership-with-microsoft-the-dark-side-of-the-force" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-partnership-with-microsoft-the-dark-side-of-the-force">A partnership with Microsoft: the dark side of the Force?</h4>
<p>“<em>OpenAI was about the democratization of AI power. So that’s why [it] was created as a nonprofit foundation, to ensure that AI power … or to reduce the probability that AI power would be monopolized.</em>” <a href="https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2018/11/2/18053418/elon-musk-artificial-intelligence-google-deepmind-openai">Elon Musk, in an interview</a> with Kara Swisher in 2018</p>
<p>Until very recently, OpenAI was an exception in the field of private AI. As its name suggests, almost all its work was shared on the <a href="https://github.com/openai">Github</a> platform, making it difficult to envision how the company planned to monetize its research. Could this have been a real philanthropic effort on the part of Elon Musk, always so keen to <a href="https://www.cnbc.com/2020/05/13/elon-musk-has-a-complex-relationship-with-the-ai-community.html">criticize the Google and Facebook models</a>? In any case, his attitude allowed OpenAI to catch up with the two giants by attracting ethically aware young talent. But since Microsoft became a shareholder, the paradigm shift has been brutal. Not only has OpenAI officially become a for-profit company, but most of all, contrary to its predecessor GTP-2, GTP-3 is not open at all: its code has not been published and access to this AI is very slow and non-transparent.</p>
<p>The reason invoked: the technology is too “dangerous” to be shared with the public. Reality: Microsoft’s presence in OpenAI’s capital signals a change in the business model. An ultra-powerful AI is being trained on an extremely expensive computer and people wanting to use this AI will, from now on, have to pay a subscription that will give them no access to the code or the super-computer, but only to an interface allowing them to submit requests and retrieve the corresponding results. True, a waiting line still gives some scientists or developers access to the interface for free, but it is obvious that this mainly allows OpenAI to crowdsource the search for applications of their tool. As soon as the most fruitful niches are identified and sufficiently publicized in the media, the odds are that everyone will be charged for the service.</p>
<p>It so happens that mastering such technology as GPT’3 will rapidly become synonymous with mastering the web, in the sense that it will enable studying correlations and perhaps causality links between the innumerable events that crisscross it. What will be the short, medium and long-term consequences of the Beirut explosions on public opinions? How will Brexit affect the relationship between Europeans and Britons? Are the Iranians angry enough at their government to successfully carry out a destabilization operation? Are the French for or against reelecting Macron? Which banks and companies will crumble after the pandemic? These geopolitical stakes are already at the heart of the question because artificial intelligence already has the unique capacity to link and synthesise vast and disparate amounts of data at a scale that no human being could ever attain. And for the time being, we are just talking about the ability to “see” the world through the prism of AI, not to control it – which would mean to promote one scenario over another by facilitating or limiting the transmission of certain information.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-european-lag-in-ai-and-big-data" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-european-lag-in-ai-and-big-data">The European lag in AI and Big Data</h4>
<p>Given this outlook, a technophobic setback cannot be excluded. But this might adversely affect society as a whole, because technology will continue to progress, with or without people’s consent. It seems to me that the big issue is rather that of the public control of this technology. We know that Europe lags far behind the United States and China in terms of Big Data and AI. Europe has no social network, no search engine, no e-commerce online platform, no video engine that could even attempt to compete with Facebook, Google, Amazon and Youtube. Although heightened awareness has led to advances in terms of the collection and storage of data by these companies, the issue of what they do with the data is still a secondary concern. But the fact is that even with <a href="https://ec.europa.eu/info/law/law-topic/data-protection_en">RGPD</a> filtering, even if we consider only the public web, an enormous amount of data remains accessible to AI algorithms. Simply put, OpenAI currently processes public data with a private algorithm, while Google and Facebook process private data with (relatively) public algorithms. In both cases, intelligence – in the sense of information – has been privatized. And in both cases, the huge supercomputers dedicated to data processing are inaccessible to scientists, NGO and public authorities.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/privateAI/azurefarm.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="400"></p>
<figcaption><em>Server farm of the cloud computing service Microsoft Azure in the United Kingdom</em></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>It is true that concrete applications of linguistic modeling and deep analysis of the web made possible by algorithms like GPT-3 are still incipient, but we must realize that a good part of goodInformation Research will use this type of system in the future. Instead of Google quests that return thousands of results, we will directly present our questions to a successor of GPT-3, whether we are “civilians” or researchers, journalists, or even military. Interaction with computers will become something different altogether. Whether they are super-intelligent, intelligent, conscious or not, these algorithms will become our <em>de facto</em> daily contact points in a decade, maybe two. Even though they are still anecdotal due to their limited performance, the principle is already at work in Siri or Google Voice.</p>
</section>
<section id="towards-a-public-european-ai" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="towards-a-public-european-ai">Towards a public European AI?</h4>
<p>Unlike the issues related to privacy, AI is not yet a true object of ethical debate or strategic reflection. This debate is often squeezed between two equally naïve positions: on one side, optimists trust private actors such as GAFAM to self-regulate; on the other, pessimists already envision a catastrophic future – a mix between <em>1984</em>, <em>Brave New World</em> and <em>Minority Report</em>. And in both cases, inaction wins. Will we have to wait for something as huge as the Cambridge Analytica scandal for European governments to decide that they have to deal with the issue? Focusing only on the risks related to so-called “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astroturfing">astroturfing</a>” and violations of privacy, no matter how real these are, is not enough. Even if we can limit data leaks, control their storage and limit the influence of the networks on electoral choices, we will be unable to keep China and the United States from developing more and more sophisticated artificial intelligence algorithms.</p>
<p>The only viable option seems to be entering the race and competing with the other superpowers. Given the number of European engineers working in the AI departments of Google and Facebook, we clearly have the means to do it. And at a time when Silicon Valley is implementing huge neural networks capable of digesting the whole web for commercial and perhaps <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2018/6/7/17439310/google-ai-ethics-principles-warfare-weapons-military-project-maven">military</a> purposes, we Europeans may even have the duty to do it. In plain language, this means Europe has to urgently catch up to allow artificial intelligence technologies to remain (or again become) public tools dedicated to research and the pursuit of the common good.</p>
<p>More than ever, it is necessary to envision a public and transparent AI serving knowledge and progress. The good news is that the European Union has just announced, on September 21, an eight billion euros investment plan dedicated to the acquisition of supercomputers. It now remains to be seen how these funds will be put to use.</p>
<hr>
</section>
<section id="additional-reading" class="level4">
<h4 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="additional-reading">Additional reading</h4>
<p>A comprehensive presentation of the GTP-3 Algorithm by Steve Omohundro</p>
<div class="quarto-video ratio ratio-16x9"><iframe data-external="1" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/0ZVOmBp29E0" title="" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen=""></iframe></div>
<hr>
<p>GPT-2, the predecessor of GPT-3, was used in numerous projects. Undoubtedly one of the most recreational is AIdungeon, which allows the user to directly interact with this 1.5-billion parameter neural network. The scripts of the short movies <a href="https://medium.com/merzazine/bloomsday-2020-f312be5caf94">Bloomsday</a> and <a href="https://arstechnica.com/gaming/2016/06/an-ai-wrote-this-movie-and-its-strangely-moving/">Sunsprings</a> were also generated by GPT-2.</p>
<p>Researcher Raphaël Millière used the GPT-3 algorithm to produce quite fascinating philosophical texts:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>I asked GPT-3 to write a response to the philosophical essays written about it by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/DrZimmermann?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DrZimmermann</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/rinireg?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@rinireg</a> <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/ShannonVallor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@ShannonVallor</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/add_hawk?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@add_hawk</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/AmandaAskell?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@AmandaAskell</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/dioscuri?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@dioscuri</a>, David Chalmers, Carlos Montemayor, and Justin Khoo published yesterday by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/DailyNousEditor?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@DailyNousEditor</a>. It’s quite remarkable! <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://t.co/W1PVlsHdu4">pic.twitter.com/W1PVlsHdu4</a> — Raphaël Millière (@raphamilliere) <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205030704/https://twitter.com/raphamilliere/status/1289129723310886912?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">July 31, 2020</a></p>
</blockquote>
<p>See also his <a href="https://twitter.com/raphamilliere/status/1289226960279764992">methodology</a> (notice that the algorithm was guided by the scientist), other texts on his <a href="https://twitter.com/raphamilliere">Twitter</a> account, and his detailed paper in <a href="https://syncedreview.com/2020/08/04/as-its-gpt-3-model-wows-the-world-openai-ceo-suggests-the-hype-is-way-too-much/">Synced</a> on the subject.&nbsp;</p>
<hr>
<p>– Example of a journalistic text generated by the GPT-3 algorithm:</p>
<p><strong>Title: United Methodists Agree to Historic Split</strong></p>
<p><strong>Subtitle: Those who oppose gay marriage will form their own denomination</strong></p>
<p>Article: After two days of intense debate, the United Methodist Church has agreed to a historic split – one that is expected to end in the creation of a new denomination, one that will be «theologically and socially conservative,» according to The Washington Post. The majority of delegates attending the church’s annual General Conference in May voted to strengthen a ban on the ordination of LGBTQ clergy and to write new rules that will «discipline» clergy who officiate at same-sex weddings. But those who opposed these measures have a new plan: They say they will form a separate denomination by 2020, calling their church the Christian Methodist denomination. The Post notes that the denomination, which claims 12.5 million members, was in the early 20th century the «largest Protestant denomination in the U.S.,» but that it has been shrinking in recent decades. The new split will be the second in the church’s history. The first occurred in 1968, when roughly 10 percent of the denomination left to form the Evangelical United Brethren Church. The Post notes that the proposed split «comes at a critical time for the church, which has been losing members for years,» which has been «pushed toward the brink of a schism over the role of LGBTQ people in the church.» Gay marriage is not the only issue that has divided the church. In 2016, the denomination was split over ordination of transgender clergy, with the North Pacific regional conference voting to ban them from serving as clergy, and the South Pacific regional conference voting to allow them.</p>
<p><em>The information initially given to the algorithm (title and subtitle) is at the top, in bold characters; the rest of the text was generated automatically.</em></p>
<hr>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>IA</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>cognitive sciences</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/privateAI/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2020 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/privateAI/coverIAprivee.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Could Covid-19 Have Originated on American Soil?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/uscovid/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>The hypothesis of a laboratory leak, which until a few weeks ago was immediately classified as a conspiracy theory, is now being considered by almost the entire press as a plausible explanation for the emergence of Covid-19 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.europe1.fr/sante/le-coronavirus-a-t-il-vraiment-pu-sechapper-dun-laboratoire-de-wuhan-3962623">#1</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.lexpress.fr/actualite/monde/amerique-nord/le-coronavirus-pourrait-il-provenir-d-un-laboratoire-de-wuhan_2123945.html">#2</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.bfmtv.com/international/coronavirus-quel-est-ce-laboratoire-chinois-pointe-du-doigt-par-washington-1895295.html">#3</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.francetvinfo.fr/sante/maladie/coronavirus/coronavirus-le-laboratoire-chinois-de-wuhan-pointe-du-doigt-nie-etre-a-l-origine-de-la-pandemie_3923829.html">#4</a>). Unfortunately, by focusing exclusively on the Wuhan laboratory, the French media are playing into the hands of the Trump administration and seem to forget that such a leak could have occurred anywhere in the world.</p>
<p>As I mentioned in my previous post entitled “Origins of the Pandemic: Why We Should Not Blame China” (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2020/04/17/origines-de-la-pandemie-pourquoi-faut-il-sabstenir-daccabler-la-chine/">#5</a>), the Wuhan origin of the virus remains uncertain and the United States is also on the list of potential suspects if the laboratory leak hypothesis is retained. Indeed, like China, Americans are extremely active in research on bat coronaviruses. While Ralph Baric’s laboratory at the University of North Carolina is certainly the most publicized due to controversial experiments aimed at making these viruses more aggressive to humans (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2014/12/academy-meeting-risky-virus-studies-struggles-find-common-ground">#6</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.the-scientist.com/news-opinion/lab-made-coronavirus-triggers-debate-34502">#7</a>), many other organizations are working on the subject. Beyond universities and pharmaceutical companies, coronaviruses have been studied for over ten years by the US military (more on this later) and by private entities like Ecohealth Alliance (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.ecohealthalliance.org/">#8</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.ecohealthalliance.org/2017/06/missing-viruses">#9</a>) — specializing in the discovery of new bat viruses and having published more than fifty scientific articles on the subject since 2013 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=%22ecohealth+alliance%22+bat+virus">#10</a>).</p>
<p>Today, I propose to delve deeper into this American hypothesis, hoping it will help balance the debate, which dangerously leans towards a form of primary Atlanticism tinged with conspiracy theories. But I am well aware that this is a sensitive subject, whose discourse can easily be “recovered” to fuel other conspiracy theories. This post, therefore, cannot do without a preliminary warning.</p>
<p>The facts outlined below in chronological form should in no way be interpreted as a body of evidence. They merely illustrate a hypothesis among others, which needs to be formally tested. The temporal juxtaposition of events does not imply the existence of a causal link. It is also important to avoid being convinced by the multiplication of converging information, as these pieces of information have been chosen to support the plausibility of a particular hypothesis, and thus suffer from significant selection bias. Finally, and most importantly, we must not forget that hundreds of scientific publications suggest that the emergence of the virus is most likely natural and that human error is, on the contrary, improbable. We know that humans come into contact with bats on all continents, that animal-to-human transmissions are frequent, and we understand the general mechanisms governing this process.</p>
<p>I encourage readers attracted, like myself, to the examination of alternative scenarios to differentiate between the political stakes surrounding the hypothesis of a potential laboratory escape and the medical-scientific approach for whom this hypothesis is as improbable as it is useless in terms of combating the pandemic itself. This battle is being fought in the search for effective treatments and vaccines, which do not depend on the virus’s nationality.</p>
<section id="mid-july-2019-unexplained-pneumonia-outbreak-in-virginia" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="mid-july-2019-unexplained-pneumonia-outbreak-in-virginia">Mid-July 2019: Unexplained Pneumonia Outbreak in Virginia</h3>
<p>On July 11, 2019, a pneumonia outbreak occurred in a retirement home in Virginia, on the east coast of the United States (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://abcnews.go.com/US/respiratory-outbreak-investigated-retirement-community-54-residents-fall/story?id=64275865">#11</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2019/07/17/third-person-has-died-after-respiratory-illness-outbreak-greenspring-village-fairfax-officials-say/">#12</a>). With 63 residents and 19 staff members infected (3 deaths), the event was serious enough to be reported to the Center for Disease Control (CDC), which oversees federal epidemiological surveillance. However, according to the Fairfax County report (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.fairfaxcounty.gov/health/outbreak-investigation-assisted-living-facility-springfield">#13</a>), the CDC could not isolate the cause and only found the common cold virus in a minority of patients.</p>
<p>Other similar events occurred nearby, and Virginia health services reported between 16 and 19 local respiratory disease outbreaks during the summer of 2019 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.washingtonpost.com/dc-md-va/2019/08/02/virginia-reports-higher-than-usual-number-respiratory-illnesses/">#14</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://translate.google.com/translate?hl=fr&amp;sl=en&amp;u=https://www.fredericksburg.com/news/state_region/virginia-reports-higher-than-usual-number-of-respiratory-illnesses/article_a79e92aa-b559-11e9-a09a-a3f73852ecdc.html&amp;prev=search">#15</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.whsv.com/content/news/Jump-in-respiratory-illnesses-reported-across-Virginia-513159371.html">#16</a>), which is an abnormal toll for this small East Coast state.</p>
</section>
<section id="august-2019-start-of-the-vaping-related-pneumonia-epidemic" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="august-2019-start-of-the-vaping-related-pneumonia-epidemic">August 2019: Start of the Vaping-Related Pneumonia Epidemic</h3>
<p>On July 26, 2019, CNN was the first media outlet to report 8 cases of unexplained pneumonia among teenagers and young adults in Wisconsin, near Chicago (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://edition.cnn.com/2019/07/26/health/wisconsin-8-teens-lung-damage/index.html">#17</a>). The vaping hypothesis was suggested because the usual pneumonia-causing viruses or bacteria were not found. In the absence of medical history or exposure to a virulent pathogen, this disease is very rare among young people. On August 2, the CDC used its emergency information platform to send a document to American hospitals reporting severe respiratory illnesses possibly related to vaping (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://emergency.cdc.gov/newsletters/coca/081619.htm">#18</a>). On August 3, CNN published a second article reporting 14 cases in Wisconsin and Illinois (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://edition.cnn.com/2019/08/03/health/vaping-hospitalizations-wisconsin-illinois/index.html">#19</a>).</p>
<p>This marked the beginning of an “epidemic” of vaping-related pneumonias, grouped under the term EVALI (E-cigarette or Vaping product use Associated Lung Injury). The term epidemic is used because the geographical clustering of cases and their temporal dynamics are evocative of a viral epidemic (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://coverage.bluecrossma.com/article/researchers-mine-data-explore-epidemic-vaping-illnesses">#20</a>). Indeed, the same exponential increase observed since the start of the pandemic can be seen, as evidenced by the study by Yulin Hswen and John Brownstein (<a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMc1912818">#21</a>, Boston Hospital).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/uscovid/evali_cases.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Confirmed or suspected cases of vaping-related pneumonia (July 25 - September 20, 2019). Source: Yulin Hswen and John Brownstein, <a href="https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMc1912818">New England Journal of Medicine</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The clinical manifestations of EVALI are very similar to those of Covid-19, including fever, pain, gastrointestinal issues, difficulty breathing, and a course lasting ten to fifteen days. Lung x-rays reflect this similarity, with “ground-glass opacities” found in both diseases (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ground-glass_opacity">#22</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://press.rsna.org/timssnet/media/pressreleases/14_pr_target.cfm?ID=2155">#23</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://pubs.rsna.org/doi/10.1148/radiol.2020200843">#24</a>). Although EVALI is not considered contagious unlike Covid-19, it should be noted that Covid-19’s very long incubation period makes detecting transmission chains much more difficult than for other viruses.</p>
<p>Studies quickly launched by the CDC suggested that EVALI might be caused by the presence of vitamin E in some vaping mixtures, especially those containing THC (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/basic_information/e-cigarettes/severe-lung-disease.html">#25</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa1916433">#26</a>). However, according to the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), this ingredient was found in only 50% of the products examined (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.fda.gov/news-events/public-health-focus/lung-injuries-associated-use-vaping-products">#27</a>), and the epidemic could not be associated with the appearance of a new product introduced to the market in the summer of 2019. Moreover, the existence of a causal link between vitamin E and pneumonia remains uncertain for methodological reasons.</p>
<p>As of December 19, 2019, there were already more than 2,500 cases and 54 deaths related to EVALI in the United States (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.npr.org/2019/12/19/789892785/vaping-related-lung-injuries-climb-past-2-500-and-54-deaths">#28</a>). While the CDC published reassuring figures in January 2020 showing a sharp decline in the curve, the decrease observed from late September is probably due to two effects: the delay in reporting information to the federal level and the change in criteria defining the disease, which became stricter on September 18 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.cdc.gov/tobacco/basic_information/e-cigarettes/assets/2019-Lung-Injury-Surveillance-Case-Definition-508.pdf">#29</a>). However, the criteria used allow any pneumonia occurring up to 90 days after a vaping experience to be associated with EVALI, which is extremely flexible and allows the inclusion of many patients who vape only rarely. <strong>The point is not to identify Covid-19 with EVALI, nor to deny that EVALI exists as such</strong>, but simply to point out that epidemiological surveillance mechanisms may have malfunctioned due to the co-occurrence of two independent problems with overlapping clinical manifestations.</p>
</section>
<section id="late-november-the-flu-season-begins-particularly-early-in-the-united-states" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="late-november-the-flu-season-begins-particularly-early-in-the-united-states">Late November: The Flu Season Begins Particularly Early in the United States</h3>
<p>Following the vaping-associated pneumonia epidemic came the flu epidemic, well known for generating symptoms similar to Covid-19, including respiratory difficulties that can lead to pneumonia. In late November - early December 2019, many regions reported the early onset of flu-like symptoms and respiratory illnesses (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://time.com/5746409/early-flu-season-2019-2020/">#30</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.beckershospitalreview.com/quality/flu-activity-supasses-national-baseline-highest-of-the-season.html">#31</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.loopnewsbarbados.com/content/wards-geriatric-hospital-limits-due-respiratory-illness">#32</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.healthline.com/health-news/what-to-know-about-the-flu-season-right-now#Here-are-the-main-strains">#33</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.wpxi.com/news/top-stories/western-pennsylvania-seeing-spike-flu-cases-so-far-this-season-health-officials-say/GJFP6OZERZBFPBFVVHQWPOGMGY/">#34</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.wbay.com/content/news/Going-viral-Local-clinics-flooded-with-flu-viruses-and-stomach-bugs-566520271.html">#35</a>). Federal data indicates that the flu epidemic started almost a month earlier this year (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://time.com/5746409/early-flu-season-2019-2020/">#36</a>) and that excess mortality was observed compared to previous years (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/#S2">#37</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/uscovid/fluseason.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="486"></p>
<figcaption>Percentage of visits for flu-like symptoms late 2019, early 2020. Source: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.cdc.gov/flu/weekly/#S2">Center for Disease Control</a>.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Unlike EVALI, the flu can be formally tested. However, looking closely at the data, the number of samples collected is tiny compared to the number of cases reported (hundreds out of hundreds of thousands of cases), and only 10 to 15% of samples show a flu virus infection (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://time.com/5746409/early-flu-season-2019-2020/">#38</a>).</p>
<p>From the perspective of an American origin preceding the explosion of cases in Wuhan, it is conceivable that the EVALI and flu epidemics contributed to Covid-19 going unnoticed by the authorities.</p>
</section>
<section id="january-2020-official-arrival-of-covid-19-on-american-soil-and-scandal-related-to-defective-tests" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="january-2020-official-arrival-of-covid-19-on-american-soil-and-scandal-related-to-defective-tests">January 2020: Official Arrival of Covid-19 on American Soil and Scandal Related to Defective Tests</h3>
<p>On January 20, 2019, Covid-19 officially made its appearance on American soil (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.nejm.org/doi/full/10.1056/NEJMoa2001191">#40</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://time.com/5759289/wuhan-pneumonia-outbreak-disease/">#41</a>). The CDC announced the first positive result. This institution being the only one authorized by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA), all initial tests were conducted internally. But faced with growing demand, the CDC announced it would begin sending test kits to various hospitals across the country on January 27 and simultaneously put its protocol online (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.genomeweb.com/pcr/cdc-provides-test-protocol-novel-coronavirus-preps-kits-local-use#.Xp2zEMhKiUk">#42</a>). A week later, the kits were finally sent in very limited quantities (about 200; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.cdc.gov/media/releases/2020/p0206-coronavirus-diagnostic-test-kits.html">#43</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/fda-takes-significant-step-coronavirus-response-efforts-issues-emergency-use-authorization-first">#44</a>).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, as early as February 12, numerous press articles indicated that the kits in question were defective and their results would be uninterpretable (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.nytimes.com/2020/02/12/health/coronavirus-test-kits-cdc.html">#45</a>), a problem recognized the following day by the CDC, which announced it would send replacement kits (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://edition.cnn.com/2020/02/13/health/us-coronavirus-test-kits/index.html">#46</a>). Yet, two long weeks later, the United States had only tested 426 people, while South Korea had already tested 35,000 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/feb/28/working-coronavirus-test-kits-promised-soon-in-all-us-states-after-faults-found">#47</a>).</p>
<p>At the time when Trump announced that the epidemic was “under control” and insisted in the media on defending the government’s actions as “appropriate” (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2020/2/25/21152514/trump-coronavirus-outbreak-covid-19-us-cases-vaccine">#48</a>), controversy was growing in national laboratories and research institutes, which struggled to obtain the necessary authorization to produce their own tests. The detailed article in the New Yorker on this subject is eloquent: it was not until February 29 that the FDA authorized a laboratory other than the CDC to diagnose Covid-19, and these authorizations were initially given sparingly due to the slow administrative system (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.newyorker.com/news/news-desk/what-went-wrong-with-coronavirus-testing-in-the-us">#49</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="april-2020-over-700000-americans-infected-by-the-virus-and-unanswered-questions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="april-2020-over-700000-americans-infected-by-the-virus-and-unanswered-questions">April 2020: Over 700,000 Americans Infected by the Virus and Unanswered Questions</h3>
<p>Two months later, the United States is one of the nations most affected by the epidemic (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.worldometers.info/coronavirus/">#50</a>). This catastrophic toll is partly explained by the superpower’s inability to develop an effective test before the end of February, even though the necessary technology has been used for twenty years in countless laboratories around the world (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://jme.bioscientifica.com/view/journals/jme/25/2/169.xml">#51</a>).</p>
<p>The numerous infection clusters that went unnoticed by the CDC obviously contributed to this rapid evolution. But given the detailed chronology above, one can legitimately wonder how long Covid-19 has been present on American soil. Is it possible that the epidemic began in the United States through short transmission chains, in Virginia and neighboring states, before disguising itself as a vaping-related pneumonia epidemic with clinical manifestations similar to Covid-19?</p>
<p>In theory, these questions could receive a positive answer if the suspected pneumonia cases mentioned above were retrospectively tested for Covid-19. It is even conceivable that the CDC questioned the link between the Covid-19 epidemic and the vaping-related pneumonia epidemic. However, if the test results performed at the beginning of the pandemic cannot be interpreted due to the technical errors that are now causing a scandal, this question may remain unanswered forever.</p>
<p>To insinuate that it might not be in the American administration’s interest to reveal such results would be to make an accusation without basis here. However, if we accept the hypothesis of an American origin, nothing prevents us from examining potential triggering events.</p>
<p>Of course, nothing excludes an animal-to-human transmission on American soil, as American bats also constitute — like their African, European, or Chinese counterparts — a reservoir of coronaviruses (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2857301/">#52</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3810755/">#53</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.microbiologyresearch.org/content/journal/jgv/10.1099/vir.0.054841-0?crawler=true">#54</a>). However, if the virus emerged naturally, it is much more plausible that the event occurred in China due to the proximity between Covid-19 and a bat coronavirus discovered on Chinese territory (the famous BatCov-RaTG13).</p>
<p>In other words, if we turn to the West, it makes sense to examine the possibility of human error, and in particular, the possibility of an incident involving the USAMRIID laboratories based at Fort Detrick (Maryland).</p>
</section>
<section id="back-to-august-2019-sudden-closure-of-the-fort-detrick-laboratory" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="back-to-august-2019-sudden-closure-of-the-fort-detrick-laboratory">Back to August 2019: Sudden Closure of the Fort Detrick Laboratory</h3>
<p>On August 2, 2019, the CDC ordered the sudden closure of the P3 and P4 laboratories at Fort Detrick in Maryland (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://translate.google.com/translate?hl=fr&amp;sl=en&amp;u=https://www.fredericknewspost.com/news/health/fort-detrick-lab-shut-down-after-failed-safety-inspection-all-research-halted-indefinitely/article_767f3459-59c2-510f-9067-bb215db4396d.html&amp;prev=search">#55</a>), two weeks after the suspicious pneumonia outbreak that opened the above chronology. At Fort Detrick, located just 65 kilometers from the Greenspring retirement home, the US military conducts research on the world’s most dangerous infectious agents, including the plague bacillus and the Ebola virus. Many American media outlets reported this information and reminded readers that Fort Detrick is known not only for its historical role in American bioweapon programs but also for its probable involvement in the anthrax-contaminated letters scandal in September 2001 (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enveloppes_contamin%C3%A9es_au_bacille_du_charbon">#56</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.the-scientist.com/news-opinion/cdc-shuts-down-army-labs-disease-research-66235">#57</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/05/health/germs-fort-detrick-biohazard.html">#58</a>).</p>
<p>The problem detected by the authorities was apparently multifactorial, without a clear indication of which factor led to the site’s closure: some procedures did not meet established standards, some personnel had not received adequate training, and a flaw was discovered in the water decontamination system. This flaw apparently dated back to May 2018, when floods damaged the institute’s water circuit (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/http://www.wfmd.com/2018/06/01/ft-detrick-making-repairs-to-steam-sterilization-plant/">#59</a>), meaning more than a year of research was conducted under defective safety conditions.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/uscovid/fortdetrick.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="492"></p>
<figcaption>USAMRIID Research Center at Fort Detrick. Source: Wikimedia Commons.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Without going into detail, it should also be noted that these anomalies occurred in a very particular context: a legal battle between Battelle Memorial Institute — the private company operating the site — and Laulima Government Solutions regarding the management of the site’s decontamination process (see the US government’s decision in this dispute: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.gao.gov/assets/710/704216.pdf">#60</a>). In October 2019, Laulima, which proposed a $150 million project against $190 million for Battelle, ultimately won and became responsible for decontamination, despite apparently limited experience in this area. It may seem surprising that a laboratory of such strategic importance to the US military is managed by a private company subject to profitability imperatives, but this is actually common in the United States. Battelle alone directly manages 9 major research centers on American soil (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Battelle_Memorial_Institute">#61</a>). The Fort Detrick center is managed by one of its subsidiaries, Tunnel Government Services (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jens_Kuhn">#62</a>).</p>
<p>Although coronaviruses are not Fort Detrick’s specialty, it is known that some research has recently focused on the MERS coronavirus (see this 2018 publication, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/29566060">#63</a>). It is also known that this laboratory has used advanced technology called CRISPR-Cas9 to selectively extract certain genetic sequences from several viruses, including Ebola (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.nature.com/articles/s41598-017-15416-3#Sec30">#64</a>). And not just any sequences. Indeed, the objective of the article in question was to extract sequences coding for a “furin cleavage site” which is also involved in Covid-19’s virulence and whose presence in the Covid-19 genome is considered “unexpected” by researchers (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0092867420302622">#65</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0166354220300528?via%3Dihub">#66</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0092867420303287">#67</a>).</p>
<p>Should we believe, based on this information, that Covid-19 resulted from human error at Fort Detrick and silently spread in the United States before mutating in Wuhan to eventually cause the pandemic we are facing?</p>
<p>No.&nbsp;We should continue to associate a very low probability with this hypothesis and prioritize the overwhelming consensus among researchers that the virus emerged naturally in China, following direct contamination of a human by a bat or an intermediate animal yet to be discovered.</p>
<p>At most, we can use the information reported here to avoid being blindly drawn into the strategy of Trump, Mike Pompeo, Fox News, and to a lesser extent Emmanuel Macron or other Western leaders, who are quick to insinuate that China is morally responsible for the pandemic (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2020/apr/17/pompeo-china-blocking-access-lab-suspected-coronav/">#68</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.washingtontimes.com/news/2020/apr/17/trump-confirms-us-investigating-reports-virus-came/">#69</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.foxnews.com/politics/coronavirus-wuhan-lab-china-compete-us-sources">#70</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.valeursactuelles.com/politique/macron-emet-son-tour-des-doutes-sur-la-gestion-du-coronavirus-par-la-chine-118309">#71</a>).</p>
<p>According to a 2018 report to the US Congress (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.gao.gov/assets/700/694617.pdf">#72</a>), the management of P3 and P4 laboratories is far from flawless in the United States. Source of scandals in the past, these laboratories are both older and more numerous than in China. Their operation by private companies raises doubts about their reliability in a context of cost reduction and economic difficulties exacerbated by Trump’s arrival in power (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.latimes.com/science/sciencenow/la-sci-sn-trump-budget-science-20190312-story.html">#73</a>).</p>
<p>While virus research is obviously necessary, many experts fear that some P3 and P4 laboratories are ticking time bombs (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.vox.com/future-perfect/2019/3/20/18260669/deadly-pathogens-escape-lab-smallpox-bird-flu">#80</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://thebulletin.org/2019/02/human-error-in-high-biocontainment-labs-a-likely-pandemic-threat/">#81</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/https://www.theguardian.com/science/2014/dec/04/-sp-100-safety-breaches-uk-labs-potentially-deadly-diseases">#82</a>). The Covid-19 pandemic and the suspicions it raises could thus be an opportunity for collective awareness: the gradual proliferation of these laboratories mathematically increases the risks faced by the entire planet. If Covid-19 is probably of natural origin, nothing tells us that the next pandemic will be as well. It may be time to raise the safety standards currently applied in China, the United States, and elsewhere…</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023909/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2020/04/22/origines-de-la-pandemie-lhypothese-americaine/"><strong>Original Article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>covid19</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>media</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/uscovid/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 21 Apr 2020 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/uscovid/covid19map.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Origins of the Pandemic: Why Should We Refrain from Blaming China?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/originspandemic/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As testing becomes widespread around the world, more and more data is available for so-called “<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.medecinesciences.org/en/articles/medsci/full_html/2002/09/medsci20021811p1146/medsci20021811p1146.html">phylogenetic</a>” analyses, which allow us to reconstruct the temporal evolution of Covid-19 within human populations by analyzing the mutations that gradually appear in its genome. It is a way of reconstructing the virus’s family tree <em>a posteriori</em>, assuming that each new mutation constitutes a new, well-identifiable “branch.”</p>
<p>These new analyses suggest that the scenario is probably not as simple as it first seemed, and it is premature to place the moral burden of the epidemic on China’s shoulders. Given the current scientific data, media and political spheres should exercise caution on this sensitive issue, especially as <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.lemonde.fr/international/article/2020/04/15/coronavirus-paris-exprime-son-mecontentement-aupres-de-l-ambassadeur-de-chine_6036626_3210.html">diplomatic tensions escalate</a>.</p>
<p>To recap, the scenario of an initial emergence in Wuhan is based on two main facts:</p>
<p>● The genome of Covid-19 is very close to the genome of a virus named BatCov-RatG13, which infected a bat analyzed at the Wuhan Institute of Virology. However, the bat in question was captured in 2013 in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.cell.com/current-biology/pdfExtended/S0960-9822(20)30360-2">a cave in Yunnan province</a>, located more than 1000 kilometers away.</p>
<p>● Among the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/http://thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(20)30183-5/fulltext">first recorded cases</a>, a large majority had visited the wild animal market in Wuhan. However, the first patient who tested positive had never visited the market in question.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/originspandemic/marchewuhan.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="580"></p>
<figcaption>Wuhan wild animal market (Wiki Commons)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="despite-appearances" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="despite-appearances">Despite Appearances</h3>
<p>While the consensus lasted for almost three months, it is now being challenged by several phylogenetic studies suggesting that the viral strain that spread in Wuhan is not the original source of the virus, or that it represents just one possible source among others.</p>
<p>Before delving into the subject, it must be emphasized that none of these studies question the idea that the virus originated from a bat. In fact, the bat virus initially analyzed in Wuhan is even used as a reference point in several analyses, with the goal of tracing the virus’s path from its closest known animal relative.</p>
<p>The first study casting doubt on the pandemic’s origin comes from a report published by the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.who.int/bulletin/online_first/20-253591.pdf">“Bulletin of the World Health Organization”</a> on February 24 by IBM researchers in the United States. It warns of the existence of three branches, the oldest of which includes a group of patients:</p>
<p>● who had no contact with the Wuhan market.</p>
<p>● who travel a lot</p>
<p>● who are of various nationalities</p>
<p>● who were infected by a variant spreading more slowly than the others</p>
<p>On March 5, another Sino-American study published on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.02.25.20027953v2">Medrxiv</a> reached a similar conclusion. In this study, three strains are identified and — again — the strain closest to BatCov-RatG13 is not the one found in Wuhan, but a strain initially detected in Japan, the USA, Australia, and other Chinese provinces far from Wuhan.</p>
</section>
<section id="wuhan-only-an-intermediate-step" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="wuhan-only-an-intermediate-step">Wuhan, Only an Intermediate Step?</h3>
<p>On April 8, finally, English and German researchers published the phylogenetic analysis of 160 virus genomes in the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.pnas.org/content/early/2020/04/07/2004999117">American journal PNAS</a>. Collected from all over the world, these genomes are very similar to each other, but there are still variations allowing the distinction of three main strains, A, B, and C.</p>
<p>Since the vast majority of the cases initially recorded in Wuhan belong to group B, the group B variants should be the closest to the BatCov-RatG13 strain (if the first human-animal contagion really took place in this city). However, this is not the case. In reality, the variants closest to the bat virus are those of group A, found in southern China (near Hong Kong), Japan, and the United States. Group C, finally, is the one that hit Europe hardest and seems to have emerged only in a third phase, following a mutation within group B.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/originspandemic/sousgroupes.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="610"></p>
<figcaption>The three subgroups highlighted by the German-British study. Bottom right, the bat genome, closer to group A than to group B, found in Wuhan (PNAS).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Interviewed by the Chinese television channel CGTN, Peter Forster from the University of Cambridge and the first author of the study is adamant: despite appearances, it is too early to say that the pandemic originated in Wuhan, China (see the interview in English, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://youtu.be/AQQf2yoymu0">here</a>).</p>
<p>While these studies could be partially challenged by the discovery of a virus even closer to Covid-19 than its current cousin, BatCov-RatG13, they remind us that the exact origins of the pandemic remain a mystery. If Wuhan is not the initial epicenter, where should we now look for patient zero?</p>
</section>
<section id="the-mystery-deepens" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-mystery-deepens">The Mystery Deepens</h3>
<p>Given the proximity between Covid-19 and BatCov-RatG13, the main hypothesis remains that the first human-animal contagion occurred in China, possibly in Yunnan province. In this case, the Chinese patient zero would have directly or indirectly infected a few travelers of various nationalities before the virus mutated and spread rapidly in Wuhan and then around the world.</p>
<p>However, other hypotheses cannot be ruled out. Since 2002, the possibility of a new coronavirus-related epidemic has motivated some research institutes to work on the threat. The first SARS epidemic broke out in China, and many samples were collected to isolate the viruses circulating in Chinese bats, with many institutes receiving these samples worldwide.</p>
<p>Once in these laboratories, these viruses are cultured to allow researchers to study their properties in detail. Depending on the question, cultures are conducted on either bat or human lung cells or on living animals, such as <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://journals.plos.org/plosmedicine/article%3Fid%3D10.1371/journal.pmed.0030149">primates</a> or <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.jax.org/news-and-insights/2020/february/introducing-mouse-model-for-corona-virus">mice</a>. In some P3 or P4 laboratories, these natural viruses are even directly modified to make them more aggressive — an approach that sparked <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.the-scientist.com/news-opinion/lab-made-coronavirus-triggers-debate-34502">significant controversy</a> a few years ago.</p>
<p>Despite the claims of Prof.&nbsp;Montagnier, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.valeursactuelles.com/monde/le-coronavirus-est-sorti-dun-laboratoire-de-wuhan-lexplication-choc-du-prix-nobel-de-medecine-luc-montagnier-118322">readily relayed by far-right media</a>, we know with near certainty that <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://theconversation.com/covid-19-origine-naturelle-ou-anthropique-136281">Covid-19 was never modified in a laboratory</a>. However, nothing excludes that it may have been cultured in vitro, an hypothesis acknowledged as possible in the most serious scientific publications (see for example <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.nature.com/articles/s41591-020-0820-9">this article published in Nature Medicine</a>). This type of research can inadvertently lead to the selection of viruses better able to infect human cells through a passive mechanism of “passage selection.”</p>
<p>Although the hypothesis remains unlikely, it is not excluded that Covid-19 emerged from a research laboratory, due to human error or equipment failure. If this were the case, patient zero could be Chinese, French, or American.</p>
</section>
<section id="international-tensions" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="international-tensions">International Tensions</h3>
<p>In this regard, it is obviously the Wuhan Institute of Virology — recently equipped with a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Institut_de_virologie_de_Wuhan">P4 laboratory thanks to French support</a> — that has been the subject of the first <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://fr.sputniknews.com/international/202004101043523262-le-covid-19-fabrique-en-laboratoire-le-bacteriologique-nest-pas-une-arme-interessante-dement-un/">suspicions</a>. Persevering in his strategy of stigmatizing China, Trump even <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.reuters.com/article/us-health-coronavirus-trump-china/trump-says-us-investigating-whether-virus-came-from-wuhan-lab-idUSKCN21Y01B">suggested</a> in a press conference that his administration is currently exploring this conspiracy-theorist favorite.</p>
<p>However, given recent events, the Chinese ambassador to France may not be entirely wrong, despite his <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.franceinter.fr/monde/quand-l-ambassade-de-chine-en-france-reecrit-l-histoire-du-coronavirus">critics</a>: it might be more appropriate to turn to the United States if considering the hypothesis of a laboratory escape. Indeed, in August 2019, a major security breach led to the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.nytimes.com/2019/08/05/health/germs-fort-detrick-biohazard.html">abrupt closure of many sensitive activities at Fort Detrick</a>, a major hub of the American military’s biodefense research. The sterilization process for waste produced by this research center working on the world’s most dangerous viruses malfunctioned following a 2018 flood, implying that a virus leak could have occurred. Indicating the severity of the event, partial resumption only took place on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.salon.com/2019/12/07/the-army-quietly-re-opens-its-infamous-germ-warfare-lab_partner/">December 7, 2019</a>, just before the pandemic began. The center only <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://homelandprepnews.com/stories/46681-maryland-lawmakers-applaud-cdcs-decision-to-reopen-fort-detrick-facility/">became fully operational again this month</a>. In other words, P4 labeling is not synonymous with infallibility, and the latest example comes from the United States.</p>
<p>In any case, as tensions rise and while awaiting further data, it would be prudent for journalists and politicians to adopt a more nuanced perspective on the virus’s origin. With nearly a million Chinese citizens or immigrants on its soil, France cannot afford to fall with Trump into <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-01009-0">stigmatizing China</a>. This stance is all the more condemnable as phylogenetic analyses cast doubt on the true origins of the pandemic.</p>
<p>Without providing definitive answers.</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205031119/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2020/04/17/origines-de-la-pandemie-pourquoi-faut-il-sabstenir-daccabler-la-chine/"><strong>Original Article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>covid19</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>media</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/originspandemic/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 16 Apr 2020 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/originspandemic/chauvesouris.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Didier Raoult Accused of Scientific Fraud: What Should We Believe?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/raoultfraud/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Since the beginning of the Covid-19 crisis, Professor Didier Raoult has established himself as an essential figure in the public debate through forceful statements and extensive interviews.</p>
<p>Unsurprisingly, the publication of the results of his study evaluating the effectiveness of a treatment combining chloroquine and azithromycin received significant media attention. Given Professor Raoult’s controversial reputation and the sensitive nature of the study, it is not surprising that the scientific community also scrutinized the results with a particularly critical eye.</p>
<p>Approved on March 6, submitted on March 16, and published on March 20, this study is currently the subject of accusations of negligence or even scientific fraud by several researchers and science journalists. Among them, the tenacious Leonid Schneider — who was already at the origin of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Catherine_Jessus#Affaire_de_m%C3%A9conduite_scientifique">the Catherine Jessus case in 2017</a> — published a particularly harsh blog post against Professor Raoult. As in the Jessus case, this new <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://forbetterscience.com/2020/03/26/chloroquine-genius-didier-raoult-to-save-the-world-from-covid-19/?fbclid=IwAR0KXLuANcVozIE_P6EpSY5O0p0DgkN4pTXtGm6htfhqt1L5l5Joe76xKsw">post</a> mixes proven facts, ad hominem attacks, and “evidence” of scientific fraud.</p>
<p>In the face of what can only be called a torrent of mud, what should we believe?</p>
<section id="personal-attacks-fraud-accusations-and-methodological-criticisms" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="personal-attacks-fraud-accusations-and-methodological-criticisms">Personal Attacks, Fraud Accusations, and Methodological Criticisms</h3>
<p>As is often the case in such situations, there are objective facts, hypotheses to verify, and contextual elements that contribute to painting an unnecessarily dark picture.</p>
<p>I will not dwell on the second part of Schneider’s post, which accuses Professor Didier Raoult of being a torturer who does not hesitate to publicly humiliate his students, a misogynist who tried to cover up a sexual harassment case within his institute, and an early climate change skeptic. Given his <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://www.francetvinfo.fr/sante/maladie/coronavirus/coronavirus-qui-est-didier-raoult-la-star-mondiale-de-la-microbiologie-qui-assure-avoir-trouve-le-remede-contre-le-covid-19_3884387.html">overinflated ego</a> and his tendency to denigrate his peers, it is not surprising that Professor Raoult has made many enemies, and it is not for me to judge the veracity of the facts presented, as concerning as they appear. But if we want to portray the man behind the researcher, we must not forget that we are still talking about a doctor who has dedicated his life to treating patients and advancing infectiology.</p>
<p>Among the hypotheses to be verified are several serious accusations of scientific fraud related to recent publications co-signed by Professor Raoult. However, image manipulations and sequencing errors will need to be thoroughly investigated before being considered as proof of fraud. Additionally, Professor Raoult is only an intermediate author on most of these studies: given the enormous number of articles he publishes each year, it is highly unlikely that these errors — if proven — are the result of direct intervention on his part.</p>
<p>In my opinion, this accumulation of accusations looks more like a witch hunt than scientific criticism, and it obscures the essential question: should we place our hopes in the treatment proposed by Professor Didier Raoult? Here, it is no longer the statements and insinuations of Leonid Schneider that need to be examined, but the facts highlighted by other active researchers.</p>
</section>
<section id="triple-hats-and-flawed-statistics" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="triple-hats-and-flawed-statistics">Triple Hats and Flawed Statistics</h3>
<p>Before diving into the heart of the matter, it is worth noting with some discomfort that the editor-in-chief of the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://www.journals.elsevier.com/international-journal-of-antimicrobial-agents">journal</a> where the article was published is none other than Jean-Marc Rolain, who is also a co-author and subordinate of Professor Raoult at the IHU Méditerranée. Such triple roles are generally frowned upon in the academic world because it becomes difficult to believe in an impartial and unbiased evaluation of the scientific quality of the work reported.</p>
<p>Most of the criticisms have been posted on the site <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://pubpeer.com/publications/B4044A446F35DF81789F6F20F8E0EE">Pubpeer</a> (a platform for post-publication peer review) or on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://www.medrxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.03.16.20037135v1">MedRxiv</a> (a preprint server for health sciences). However, one should first look at the very concise report posted by three British researchers on the site <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://zenodo.org/record/3724167#.Xn92T4j7SUm">Zenodo</a>. Proof of the attention it garnered, this report was downloaded over 18,000 times in five days.</p>
<p>The report’s authors first indicate that the paper underwent virtually no modifications between its posting on MedRxiv and its “official” publication in Jean-Marc Rolain’s journal. This means that the reviewers responsible for identifying any methodological issues found none, or their criticisms were ignored.</p>
<p>However, the criticisms are numerous and often legitimate:</p>
<p>• The statistical analyses reported in the paper are flawed because age and symptom differences between the tested groups were not accounted for. That said, a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://nfaivre.netlify.com/files/master.html">reanalyis of the data</a> shows that the main effects hold when these variables are considered.</p>
<p>• The possible (and likely) existence of biases in how patient groups were constituted. Thus, the control group patients (i.e., without treatment) were not all treated by Professor Raoult’s institute, unlike the patients receiving chloroquine. However, since the control group patients were on average younger and less often male, this lack of randomization probably does not invalidate the study’s conclusions on its own.</p>
<p>• More problematic is that Professor Raoult’s team excluded six patients from the treatment group post hoc. Among them, one death, three patients admitted to intensive care, one patient with nausea, and one patient who “left the hospital.” This is serious because at least four of these patients can be considered therapeutic failures. Excluding them could have significantly skewed the statistical conclusions given the small sample sizes tested.</p>
<p>• Finally, and most importantly, the report’s authors and many other scientists point to the absence of proper clinical data on patient outcomes. The only variable considered is viral load, so it is exaggerated and even dishonest to loudly proclaim, based on this study alone, that the combination of chloroquine and azithromycin constitutes a treatment for the disease. To date, the only <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/http://www.zjujournals.com/med/EN/10.3785/j.issn.1008-9292.2020.03.03#1">other publication</a> evaluating chloroquine’s effectiveness suggests that it has no effect, taken alone, on clinical outcomes. It is therefore possible that Professor Raoult’s treatment makes the virus undetectable in the upper airways (where the samples are taken) without eradicating it from the rest of the body (notably the lungs).</p>
</section>
<section id="a-deplorable-media-strategy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-deplorable-media-strategy">A Deplorable Media Strategy</h3>
<p>These criticisms suggest that Professor Raoult and his team’s recommendations are very premature, and certain irregularities highlighted — both in the British researchers’ report and on Pubpeer — suggest that the analyses fall far short of the standards expected given the severity of the crisis and the therapeutic directions that might be taken in response to the infectious disease specialist’s media campaign.</p>
<p>Of course, the health emergency justifies the rapid publication of the most promising scientific results. That is not the question. Nor is it a question of who Professor Raoult really is. What matters now is that the public debate can take place in good conditions without anyone using the crisis to put themselves in the spotlight.</p>
<p>There is thus reason to be annoyed by Professor Raoult’s explosive and immodest positions, as he is quick to self-congratulate and disqualify the work of his peers.</p>
<p>And there is reason to lament, conversely, the little attention received by the Academy of Medicine, which considers that “the public release of hydroxychloroquine for hospitalized patients in respiratory distress is not an appropriate response for patients whose viral load is, at this stage, mostly nonexistent and whose illness is no longer a strictly viral disease but a pulmonary failure” (official statement, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/http://www.academie-medecine.fr/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/20.3.26-Communiqu%C3%A9-Anm-AnP-Chloroquine.pdf?fbclid=IwAR0JDrgql1A2se6XKhzcatX6a6HS8KfSVOoXetI_e0mnU3F46P4vA-HnMaM">here</a>).</p>
</section>
<section id="further-reading" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="further-reading">Further Reading</h3>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://www.heidi.news/articles/coronavirus-didier-raoult-enfonce-le-clou-avec-une-deuxieme-publication-sur-la-chloroquine?fbclid=IwAR12JA0ZUX6fU-x38-uNfPDxAKHxwOE_wfOa-afqmiH7CNROSUBml7-u_zg">Analysis</a> of the latest paper published on Saturday, March 28, by Professor Raoult’s team, still inconclusive despite the inclusion of a larger number of patients.</p>
<p>Illustration, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/https://www.instagram.com/antoinedoreart/?hl=fr">Antoine Doré</a></p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205015421/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2020/03/28/didier-raoult-accuse-de-fraude-scientifique-que-faut-il-croire/"><strong>Original Article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>covid19</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/raoultfraud/</guid>
  <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/raoultfraud/dore_virus.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Towards Self-Assessment and Horizontal Resource Control in Academia?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/autoevaluationresearch/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Recently, a group of French researchers published an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/idees/article/2020/01/20/nous-chercheurs-voulons-defendre-l-autonomie-de-la-recherche-et-des-formations_6026543_3232.html">op-ed in Le Monde</a> announcing their collective intention to apply for the presidency of the HCERES, France’s highest public authority for regulating and guiding research. This initiative, notably driven by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/http://rogueesr.fr/">rogueESR</a>, has garnered over 5000 supports, including mine.</p>
<p>Responsible for evaluating all research laboratories in France, the HCERES and its predecessor, the AERES, have accompanied—and often encouraged—the transformation of the French scientific landscape since 2006. Indeed, this “High Committee for the Evaluation of Research and Higher Education” is historically linked to the creation of the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Agence_nationale_de_la_recherche">ANR</a> (National Research Agency), which shifted French research toward an Anglo-Saxon “project-based” funding system in 2005.</p>
<section id="a-system-under-critique-for-15-years" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-system-under-critique-for-15-years">A System Under Critique for 15 Years</h3>
<p>This significant structural reform has provoked much discussion and exertion over the past 15 years. Indeed, it involves researchers dedicating a significant portion of their time to drafting funding applications that have little chance of success. Despite slight improvements since 2015, the success rate remains <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://twitter.com/Alexis_Verger/status/1150661972301701120">around 15%</a>, with many agreeing that the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0118494">time lost</a> writing and evaluating these funding applications is largely counterproductive, both scientifically and economically, given the ANR’s enormous <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/http://lesupenmaintenance.blogspot.com/2017/07/inefficience-et-couts-caches-du-neo.html">operational costs</a>.</p>
<p>In this context, the op-ed published in Le Monde at the beginning of 2020 is just the latest in a long series (see <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lepoint.fr/debats/tribune-il-faut-repenser-et-renforcer-l-agence-nationale-pour-la-recherche-08-01-2016-2008132_2.php">here</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/sciences/article/2015/09/21/recherche-la-selection-par-l-excellence-est-denaturee_4766031_1650684.html">here</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/sciences/article/2019/03/06/le-financement-de-la-recherche-fondamentale-ne-doit-pas-etre-une-loterie_5431902_1650684.html">here</a>, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.liberation.fr/debats/2019/09/02/le-jeu-du-hasard-et-de-la-recherche_1748859">here</a>, or <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.latribune.fr/opinions/20100325trib000491876/depenser-plus-pour-faire-moins-de-recherche-.html">there</a>). Will it have as much impact as the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/blog/huet/2016/06/09/politique-de-la-recherche-demission-de-masse-a-lanr/">mass resignation</a> of prominent ANR figures in 2016, who, refusing to cope with continuous <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/idees/article/2016/05/23/coupes-budgetaires-dans-la-recherche-huit-grands-chercheurs-denoncent-un-suicide-scientifique-et-industriel_4924612_3232.html">budget cuts</a> under Sarkozy and Hollande, perhaps helped increase the overall budget dedicated to the structure?</p>
<p>It’s uncertain, especially considering how the current executive treats demands coming “from below” and considering that the likely candidate for the presidency of the HCERES is none other than <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/blog/huet/2020/01/21/montee-de-la-contestation-a-luniversite-et-au-cnrs/">Thierry Coulhon</a>, a former advisor to the Fillon government and now advising Emmanuel Macron on “education, higher education, research, and innovation”.</p>
<p>However, the unprecedented interest of this op-ed paradoxically lies in reminding us of a very simple but often forgotten fact: in terms of research evaluation, “the bottom” is actually “the top” since no one is better placed to assess scientific output than the researchers themselves. They are the ones, not ministers or the President, who are best positioned to anticipate upcoming revolutions, determine which research lines are dead ends and which are promising, or to evaluate the material and human resources required to achieve set goals.</p>
<p>With this idea in mind, members of the rogueESR collective urge the entire scientific community to engage with the question in their latest letter:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>The second phase of this nascent movement of reaffirming the scholarly world as forming a community capable of setting its own rules, this immense freedom being balanced by a principle of responsibility towards society, requires everyone’s participation. What strategy can we employ, by curbing all forms of bureaucracy, to agree, beyond partisan divisions, on the University and the research system we aspire to bring to life. Our email is open to all thoughtful tactical and strategic proposals.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I seize the opportunity to submit a proposal as radically different from the current system as from the previous one. Given the ANR’s programmed failure, it might be tempting to nostalgically contemplate the past and its “inter-ministerial funding”—less time-consuming and more flexible for researchers—but this would be a serious mistake, in my opinion.</p>
<p>Indeed, if one can consider that the reforms which gave birth to the ANR were an opportunity for the then-government to hold a “modernization discourse” that masked—like a smokescreen—the upcoming budget cuts, these reforms were still based on strong dissatisfaction with the old system. It is informative to revisit the report on research studied at the National Assembly on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/http://www.assemblee-nationale.fr/12/rap-info/i1998.asp">December 21, 2004</a>. Many criticisms targeted the overly hierarchical allocation of credits (following a ministry - institute - laboratory - researcher scheme) whose major flaw was to fuel local nepotisms, often allowing laboratory directors to distribute resources at their discretion; and often at the expense of the most innovative or risky projects carried by younger researchers still poorly integrated into the complex power games that academia has always known. The shift to project-based funding has at least had the virtue of de-siloing all researchers and establishing a horizontal competition theoretically allowing each to compete directly for resources.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-framework-breaking-proposal" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-framework-breaking-proposal">A Framework-Breaking Proposal</h3>
<p>Is it possible to combine the flexibility of the old system with the horizontality of the new, while taking a real step towards a more free, more creative science whose management would involve “everyone’s participation”? It seems to me that yes.</p>
<p>The idea is as follows: instead of awarding funding by project or by laboratory, the state could directly allocate a portion of its credits to each actor in the research process, according to a system blending scientific merit and seniority. From the PhD student at the end of their thesis to the senior research director, including the research engineer and the postdoc, each person contributing to advancing knowledge would thus control a fraction of the credits available for their branch.</p>
<p>At each hierarchical level, the allocation would increase significantly, reflecting despite everything the evolution of scientific expertise. In the field of cognitive neuroscience, for example, the state could allocate five thousand euros per year for doctoral students at the end of their thesis, twenty thousand euros for non-tenured researchers (i.e., postdocs), and fifty thousand euros for tenured researchers and research engineers. If this idea may seem subversive with respect to the traditional hierarchical organization, it is not by accident. In reality, it’s simply about pushing the logic of rogueESR to the limit.</p>
<p>If researchers are to collectively evaluate and control research, isn’t it natural to assign to each of them a part of the available resources, to be employed according to their expertise and motivations? Since it is common to consider that a PhD student at the end of their thesis has already become an <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.lemonde.fr/sciences/article/2014/05/05/tribune-qui-fait-la-recherche-publique-en-france_4411829_1650684.html">expert</a> regarding their research theme, and since postdocs are often seen as true <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://academic.oup.com/bioscience/article/65/11/1088/374441">locomotives</a> of academia, isn’t it sensible to include these two categories in the collective system of evaluation and control being discussed?</p>
<p>A natural objection is that this organization seems at first glance highly individualistic, each researcher then having their little patch of land to cultivate their particular interests. However, it should be noted that the project-based funding as we know it is already highly individualistic since the funding is associated with a single person rather than a collective, both at the French and European levels. Moreover, in this new system, no one would have the “firepower” necessary to carry out major projects, so that collaboration and pooling of resources would be imposed on anyone with big scientific ambitions.</p>
<p>By setting up a platform allowing both the submission of projects, the call for contributions, and the allocation of resources, each actor could then organize a fundraising campaign among their peers, in exchange for an authorship place and/or a proportionate right to oversee the publications resulting from this pooling. The state could promote this type of cooperative logic by awarding additional funding to projects that have received enough contributions, thus breaking with the zero-sum game principle.</p>
</section>
<section id="fighting-academic-branding-and-the-reign-of-researcher-communicators" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="fighting-academic-branding-and-the-reign-of-researcher-communicators">Fighting Academic “Branding” and the Reign of Researcher-Communicators</h3>
<p>The great virtue of this system would be to put each researcher before the following dilemma: work alone with limited means or work collectively with significantly greater means, so that personal ambitions would systematically be weighed against scientific ambitions; and this, unlike the current system where building a personal reputation and brand (“<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-03021-5">academic branding</a>”) very largely conditions the ability to fulfill our scientific ambitions, benefiting the researchers most skilled in communication.</p>
<p>Such an initiative would undoubtedly multiply the inventiveness of researchers at every level and would also allow for better exploitation of the inter-individual differences that exist in academia. For example, in the field of neuroscience, as in many others, “theorists” generally do not need a lot of their own resources to do their work. A few good computers suffice. However, they urgently need to be able to rely on work informing and constraining the theories they develop. In such a system, these same theorists could thus make their credits available to “experimentalists” who have submitted the most useful projects to them, or directly issue a call for contributions for the experiments they most need.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/autoevaluationresearch/autoeval.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Proposed distribution schema</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Certainly, such a reform could not be imposed on the scientific community overnight, and it would undoubtedly take years of local experimentation to develop the necessary tools and refine the logistical and ethical aspects of this entirely “bottom-up” participative system, to borrow an Anglicism that scientists are fond of.</p>
<p>But if we want to hold all researchers accountable for the future of research, and if we want them all to intervene in its evaluation, if we want to fight both bureaucratic arbitrariness and hierarchical arbitrariness, we will have to give them the counterpart of this new responsibility: control over the available resources. Without this, a system proceeding by the nomination of representatives in charge of control, evaluation, and distribution of resources seems inevitable, whether they be laboratory directors or bureaucrats employed by central institutions like the ANR.</p>
<p>For dispensing with such representatives and for freeing the vital forces of academia while advocating self-management, it is essential that everyone contribute to this work of evaluation, orientation, and pooling.</p>
</section>
<section id="to-go-further" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="to-go-further">To Go Further</h3>
<p>As part of this collective movement, two public sessions of the “Science Policies” seminar will be held at the EHESS on January 30 and February 6 next. These meetings will undoubtedly provide an opportunity to discuss many other proposals imagined by researchers to reform the system as we know it.</p>
<p>See the program, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/https://pds.hypotheses.org/">here</a>.</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205023236/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2020/01/23/vers-lauto-evaluation-et-le-controle-horizontal-des-ressources-dans-le-monde-academique/"><strong>Original article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>economics</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/autoevaluationresearch/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jan 2020 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/autoevaluationresearch/autoeval_banner.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Brain Weather: How Our Emotions Fluctuate with the Seasons</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainweather/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>For most of us, despite the political frustrations that afflict some, summer is synonymous with good mood. This trend directly affects web platforms like Twitter, where positively connoted words become more frequent (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/http://science.sciencemag.org/content/sci/333/6051/1878.full.pdf?casa_token=00-l9mSMK0sAAAAA:rBMnpd-MAo7RUucQAz277KCsUVK0Lrw1tCM1HFd79ct_rlSSvdSy9sNPrXTLzXCc6q8BeelP7KTnoQ">Golder &amp; Maci, 2011</a>) while negatively connoted words decrease. The analysis of mood changes on the web (“<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sentiment_analysis">sentiment analysis</a>” in English) suggests that even our anxieties ease as Wikipedia searches related to various illnesses drop during the summer period.</p>
<p>What happens in our brain that might explain why our vocabulary and moods warm up as our skins caramelize? To answer this question, we must delve into a scientific field as vast as it is fascinating: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronobiologie">chronobiology</a>, which, as its etymology indicates, studies how organisms adapt to the temporal cycles of Mother Nature.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainweather/cycles.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="645"></p>
<figcaption>The analysis of internet users’ behavior on Twitter and Wikipedia illustrates mood changes throughout the year. For example, searches related to various psychiatric disorders increase in winter and early spring, just as tweets containing keywords like “anger,” “sadness,” or “anxiety” rise in autumn (Dzogang et al., 2016, see also).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>While the structure of the human brain is remarkably stable compared to that of smaller mammals (like the squirrel, whose brain shrinks by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=Profound+seasonal+changes+in+brain+size+and+architecture+in+the+common+shrew">10 to 25%</a> in winter!), most of our body systems still adapt, to varying degrees, to the differences in light, humidity, and temperature that characterize each season.</p>
<p>But in terms of the “seasonality of emotions,” it is primarily the famous <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/http://lecerveau.mcgill.ca/flash/d/d_08/d_08_m/d_08_m_dep/d_08_m_dep.html">serotonin</a> that we should look at. Involved in mood regulation, learning, appetite, and impulsivity, a series of studies demonstrates the existence of a “circannual” rhythm in this complex <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuromodulation">neuromodulator</a> which is also one of the most important therapeutic targets for contemporary psychiatry.</p>
<section id="serotonin-and-sunshine" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="serotonin-and-sunshine">Serotonin and Sunshine</h3>
<p>Thus, the membrane transporter of serotonin, which helps clear the molecule after it has been released, decreases in concentration in summer and increases in winter (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/18762593">Praschak-Rieder et al., 2008</a>; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/20110086">Kalbitzer et al., 2010</a>). This annual variation is especially relevant as it appears absent in those who suffer from <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/D%C3%A9pression_saisonni%C3%A8re">seasonal depression</a> (seasonal affective disorder in English; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26994750">McMahon et al., 2016</a>). It is striking to note that classical antidepressants mimic the effect of the sun, as they also act by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inhibiteur_s%C3%A9lectif_de_la_recapture_de_la_s%C3%A9rotonine">reducing the effectiveness of the serotonin transporter</a>.</p>
<p>Two other aspects of the system also fluctuate throughout the year: the activity of the serotonergic neurons themselves increases with day length (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25959961">Green et al., 2015</a>) as does the density of certain receptors that bridge the “serotonin signal” and our behavior (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25772667">the 5HT1A</a>, for purists). Not to mention the cycles observed in the synthesis and degradation pathways of the molecule (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://jamanetwork.com/journals/jamapsychiatry/article-abstract/497278">Maes et al., 1995</a>; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0140673602117375">Lambert et al., 2002</a>; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.nature.com/articles/tp201384">Luykx et al., 2013</a>)… More signal at the base, less evacuation, and more receptors to receive it, all point in the same direction, making it quite natural to think that the serotonergic system as a whole significantly contributes to the fluctuation of our moods, and perhaps even some of our cognitive abilities (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/?term=A+Warm+Heart+and+a+Clear+Head">Keller et al., 2005</a>; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/26858432">Meyer et al., 2016</a>)!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainweather/serosaison.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="860"></p>
<figcaption>On the left, representation of the transporter responsible for serotonin reuptake after its release (excerpt from a detailed and interesting blog post on the sometimes exaggerated role of the serotonin transporter in popularizing psychiatric disorders). On the right, fluctuation of the transporter’s expression throughout the year, with its characteristic peak in mid-winter (Kalbitzer et al., 2010).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Should we then soak up the sun in summer to charge up on good mood for the entire year? Is the phenomenon related to excessive sunbathing or the intensive use of tanning beds observed in some? It’s hard to say, especially since we don’t yet know if light has a direct impact or if the observed effects are due to another factor, which could be related to dietary changes or increased physical activity in summer.</p>
<p>It would therefore be reductive and even rash to hope to explain everything by serotonin, especially since other related chemical signals (like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/21048126">dopamine</a>) also vary with the seasons. Regarding exposure to solar or artificial UV, a recent study conducted on mice suggests that it is actually <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Endorphine">endorphins</a> that explain the development of true addictive behaviors (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/24949966">Fell et al., 2014</a>). The idea is quite simple: prolonged exposure to UV causes a series of micro-traumas to our skin, which reacts by releasing these natural painkillers known as endorphins. In turn, these endorphins induce a feeling of relaxation and well-being similar to what joggers feel after a long run. And like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0031938416300269">athletes</a>, a small proportion of individuals sensitive to this mechanism would develop a form of UV addiction that is increasingly concerning <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/28639816">in the United States</a>.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-summer-picture-not-so-rosy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-summer-picture-not-so-rosy">A Summer Picture Not So Rosy</h3>
<p>Furthermore, as often in science, what seems obvious at first glance turns out to be more complex than it appears. For example, contrary to a deeply rooted popular belief, it is not during winter that the deepest psychological distresses manifest. The vast majority of available data indicates that suicide rates actually peak <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.theguardian.com/science/2005/may/12/mentalhealth.society">at the end of spring and early summer</a>.</p>
<p>Conducted in the United States and Mexico, a study published on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.nature.com/articles/s41558-018-0222-x">July 28</a> in the journal Nature Climate Change even shows a clear correlation between suicide rates and temperature variations from one year to the next. In other words, for a given month, suicide rates increase when temperatures are above usual values. And the effect sizes are so impressive that researchers estimate that global warming could have an impact similar to that of an economic crisis by 2050: for each additional degree, the suicide rate increases by 0.7% in the US and 2.1% in Mexico. To better understand the link between these two variables, researchers then analyzed 600 million tweets posted in these two regions. Unexpectedly but consistently with epidemiological observations, this second analysis reveals a positive correlation between monthly temperature and the number of “depressive connotation tweets.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainweather/suicide_ete.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="637"></p>
<figcaption>Map showing the effect of temperatures higher (in red) or lower (in blue) than seasonal normals on suicide rates in the United States and Mexico (excerpt from Burke et al., 2018).</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>So, while summer brings its share of joys (and serotonin?) to most of us, it also represents a difficult period for vulnerable and fragile people. If the authors of the American study support the idea that the increase in suicide rates rests on a biological mechanism, they do not specify which one. In any case, it is known that summer can exacerbate social isolation, especially among those who do not have the chance to go on vacation and among the elderly (about <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201205021208/https://www.inegalites.fr/Qui-va-partir-en-vacances">40% of the population</a> in France).</p>
<p>Hence the usefulness of postcards!</p>
<p><a href="http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2017/10/14/neurosciences-contre-sciences-sociales-lerreur-de-frederic-lordon/"><strong>Original Article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>neuromodulation</category>
  <category>psychiatry</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainweather/</guid>
  <pubDate>Thu, 11 Oct 2018 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainweather/meteocerveau.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>A Remarkable Brain Factory</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Manières de voir</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/cubabrainfarm/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>“The future of our country must necessarily be a future of scientists, thinkers, because that is precisely what we are sowing; we are sowing opportunities for intelligence,” proclaimed Fidel Castro on January 15, 1960. In 1959, the country had three universities, compared to more than sixty today. The literacy rate jumped from around 70% to over 99% in 2012 (the latest available figures). That of the neighboring island, Haiti, stagnates at 62%<sup>1</sup>.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn1"><p><sup>1</sup>&nbsp;On the occasion of the 20th anniversary of the Cuban Speleological Society, Academy of Sciences. <a href="http://en.granma.cu/special-in-honor-of-fidel-s-90th-birthday/2016-08-12/a-talent-for-doing-the-impossible" class="uri">http://en.granma.cu/special-in-honor-of-fidel-s-90th-birthday/2016-08-12/a-talent-for-doing-the-impossible</a></p></div><div id="fn2"><p><sup>2</sup>&nbsp;According to the United Nations Development Programme.</p></div><div id="fn3"><p><sup>3</sup>&nbsp;For example, from 2007-2012, Cuba invested 11.9% of its GDP in education, a world record.</p></div></div><p>Today, Havana exports doctors and researchers worldwide (see Hernando Calvo Ospina’s article on page 52). Cuba’s successes in the biomedical field are largely due to state efforts in public education (which represent more than 10% of the gross domestic product<sup>2</sup>). The country is now on par with the United States in terms of life expectancy (78.5 years) and infant mortality (5 per 1,000)<sup>3</sup>. Thus, doctors constitute a true economic boon for the island (the primary source of foreign exchange, ahead of remittances and tourism).</p>
<p>Thanks to a 2000 agreement with Hugo Chávez’s Venezuela, the island long received up to one hundred thousand barrels of oil per day (at subsidized prices) in exchange for which more than ten thousand Cuban doctors and academics work on Venezuelan soil<sup>4</sup>.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn4"><p><sup>4</sup>&nbsp;Statistics from the World Health Organization, 2016.</p></div></div><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/cubabrainfarm/rue.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Tomás Munita. — Street scene in downtown Havana, 2016</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Director of the Cuban Neuroscience Center (CNEURO) in Havana, Dr.&nbsp;Mitchell Valdés-Sosa, 67, has been a privileged witness to the history of Cuban science development. Exiled to Chicago under the dictatorship of Fulgencio Batista (1952-1959), his father returned to the island in 1961 to practice obstetrics and address the exodus of the medical bourgeoisie fleeing the revolution<sup>5</sup>. He witnessed the creation of the Centro Nacional de Investigaciones Científicas (CNIC, equivalent to the National Center for Scientific Research, CNRS) in 1965, the arrival of numerous researchers and doctors sent by the USSR of Leonid Brezhnev or Chile of Salvador Allende to train the first generation of local specialists, and the defense of the island’s first PhD in 1971. In the early 1980s, Cuban research moved away from the Soviet model, deemed too centralized, too bureaucratic, and too rigid. The government increasingly granted autonomy to researchers whom it consulted frequently.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn5"><p><sup>5</sup>&nbsp;It is estimated that Cuba lost more than a third of its doctors between 1959 and 1961.</p></div></div><p>During the prosperous years preceding perestroika and the “special period,” Valdés-Sosa and his brother Pedro contributed to some of the major achievements in local neuroscience, such as building the first Cuban computer-assisted brain imaging system and designing algorithms for processing neural signals still used today.</p>
<div class="line-block"><strong>China, a privileged partner of the island, has just been authorized to open a pharmaceutical company on the territory</strong></div>
<p>The budget for Cuban research remains limited. Thus, the government promotes short circuits in which fundamental research, applied research, and production chains are concentrated in one place. For instance, CNEURO brings together biologists, mathematicians, physicists, doctors involved in various clinical trials, and several specialized technicians. Valdés-Sosa proudly notes that CNEURO produces “some six thousand prostheses and hearing aids each year, allowing for early diagnosis of deafness in very young children.”</p>
<p>BioCubaFarma, the public company that encompasses all actors in the biomedical industry, holds over two thousand patents and exports several hundred different products to Brazil, Vietnam, South Africa, Venezuela, Algeria, and Iran. China, a privileged partner of Cuba, has just been authorized to open a pharmaceutical company on Cuban territory. Given the low cost and good training of health professionals in Cuba, Canadians are also interested, as are some French companies.</p>
<p>Cancer Vaccine Since the December 2014 agreements that led to the reopening of the US embassy in Havana and a thaw in relations between the United States and Cuba, two promising Cuban molecules have been undergoing clinical trials in the United States: a lung cancer vaccine and a drug for diabetic gangrene<sup>6</sup>. In return, administrative easing was supposed to allow American companies to export a broader range of products to Cuba, until Mr.&nbsp;Donald Trump backtracked in Miami on June 16, 2017. While the academic world enthusiastically welcomed these agreements that lay the groundwork for scientific cooperation between the two countries, there is still a long way to go. Washington never forgets to remind that “Cuba is a dictatorship,” and the Congress recently invoked the Cuba Democracy Act (1992) to impose a contractual clause enjoining Cuban pediatricians not to use American equipment they receive to torture their patients<sup>7</sup>… This provoked the indignation of doctors and researchers.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn6"><p><sup>6</sup>&nbsp;Cohen et al., 2015. <em>Advancing neuroscience interactions with Cuba</em>. Proceedings of the National Academy of Science (<a href="http://escholarship.org/uc/item/4j78s4wb">link</a>)</p></div><div id="fn7"><p><sup>7</sup>&nbsp;See the article in <em>Science</em>, which mentions the previous difficulties associated with exporting biomedical equipment. <a href="http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2014/12/researchers-applaud-us-cuba-accord" class="uri">http://www.sciencemag.org/news/2014/12/researchers-applaud-us-cuba-accord</a></p></div></div><div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/cubabrainfarm/placerevolution.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="500"></p>
<figcaption>Tomás Munita. — Revolution Square, Havana, 2014</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>However, despite the altruistic vocation<sup>8</sup> of the “revolutionary medicine” initially promoted by Ernesto “Che” Guevara, the Cuban scientific system is not without contradictions. Doctors are often sent abroad as part of a two-year civic service, during which they are housed in closely monitored camps and are required not to leave their assigned region under penalty of sanctions. Not to mention the measures devised by Washington to motivate would-be deserters<sup>9</sup>, whose remuneration is around 60 euros per month (they receive several hundred euros when on mission abroad).</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn8"><p><sup>8</sup>&nbsp;Source: <a href="https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/31/515.559" class="uri">https://www.law.cornell.edu/cfr/text/31/515.559</a></p></div><div id="fn9"><p><sup>9</sup>&nbsp;Like when Cuba sent more than 400 doctors to combat the Ebola epidemic on African soil.</p></div></div><div class="line-block"><strong>The government has launched a census program for twins to better predict the onset of certain diseases</strong></div>
<p>In addition to uncertainties related to the Trump administration’s reluctance towards US-Cuban trade and tourism, the hopes following the opening of the biomedical sector are “darkened by financial difficulties,” explains Pascal Belin, research director at the Timone Neuroscience Institute (INT) in Marseille. Belin, who has been collaborating with his counterparts in Havana for over ten years, believes that Cuban laboratories are full of “talented researchers who would make excellent additions to French institutions,” but their development depends, according to him, on the establishment of international partnerships, particularly focused on the exchange of skills and equipment. Not to mention more flexible emigration procedures on the Cuban side.</p>
<p>While the INT donated an electroencephalogram device to Dr.&nbsp;Valdés-Sosa’s team, Belin notes that other countries are ahead of France in the field of cooperation with Cuba. Maastricht University (Netherlands), for example, offered an MRI scanner worth several million euros to CNEURO and created a joint doctoral program that benefits from Cuba’s expertise in so-called “multimodal” neuroimaging<sup>10</sup>.</p>
<div class="no-row-height column-margin column-container"><div id="fn10"><p><sup>10</sup>&nbsp;Combination of several simultaneous brain activity measurements, such as electroencephalogram and MRI</p></div></div><p>To better predict the onset and progression of neurodegenerative diseases, such as Alzheimer’s — increasingly common due to the aging population — the Cuban government launched in 2004 a vast program to census all the twins on the island. With almost all (95%) of them recorded, over a hundred thousand individuals can now be mobilized to study genetic heredity and gene-environment interactions in one of the most racially diverse countries. In the specific field of cognitive neuroscience, a long-term partnership with Cuba would offer the possibility of thoroughly examining the intercultural differences between European countries and one of the last communist societies, paving the way for a better understanding of the complex dynamics governing the relationship between social structures and individual behaviors.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/mav/155/LIGNEUL/57921#nb6"><strong>Original article (Wayback Archive)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>




 ]]></description>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>research</category>
  <category>cuba</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/cubabrainfarm/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 04 Nov 2017 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/cubabrainfarm/cover.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="95" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Presidential Elections and Filter Bubbles: Scrutinizing Facebook’s Political Referencing</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>With over <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.blogdumoderateur.com/chiffres-facebook/">30 million registered users</a> in France, the web giant has become an indispensable tool for politicians, activists, and journalists shaping our democracy. The information circulated there significantly influences the evolution (or stagnation) of our political opinions and our perception of the voting intentions of our social circle.</p>
<p>Since 2013, the platform’s initial algorithm, known as <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/EdgeRank">Edge Rank</a>, has been replaced by several much more complex artificial intelligence algorithms: at its introduction, a Facebook engineer estimated that about <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://marketingland.com/edgerank-is-dead-facebooks-news-feed-algorithm-now-has-close-to-100k-weight-factors-55908">100,000 factors</a> were taken into account to determine which content would be shown to a given user. As I already wrote in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://tempsreel.nouvelobs.com/rue89/rue89-parti-pris/20151117.RUE1354/changez-votre-photo-de-profil-facebook-et-le-bleu-blanc-rouge-en-un-clic.html">November 2015 after the Paris attacks</a>, there are no reasons other than conspiracy theories to think that Facebook uses its incredible power of influence to knowingly sway the evolution of contemporary societies.</p>
<p>However, there are also very few means for citizens and public institutions to exclude such a hypothesis, since the content referencing procedure employed by Facebook is not made public, only a minority of shared content is accessible beyond “friend circles” (unlike Twitter, for example), and it is impossible to display these contents in a truly chronological order, which would facilitate the examination of its operation and any potential representation biases among users.</p>
<p>What will be the impact of this “intelligent” filtering on the 2017 presidential elections? No one can say for certain, but this should not prevent us from asking the question.</p>
<section id="experimenting-on-facebook-or-the-reign-of-system-d" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="experimenting-on-facebook-or-the-reign-of-system-d">Experimenting on Facebook or the Reign of System-D</h3>
<p>Thus, only the goodwill of citizens willing to coordinate to conduct experiments on the social network allows for the study and monitoring of how the company controls the transmission of information shared there. It is precisely the results of such an initiative that I report here (Figure 1).</p>
<p>In order to see whether Facebook favors certain presidential candidates and to what extent the “filter bubble” effect that locks us into our own political preferences is real, I asked 30 Facebook users to successively post five messages of support for the 5 main presidential candidates: Jean-Luc Mélenchon (JLM), Benoît Hamon (BH), Emmanuel Macron (EM), François Fillon (FF), and Marine Le Pen (MLP). All the messages were formatted as follows:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>That’s it, I’ve decided. In the presidential elections, I will vote for XXXXX!<br>
This is an experiment, not spam. To participate (1 to 5 min) click here: <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://goo.gl/forms/uGy3dRtxu11xKwSe2">https://goo.gl/forms/uGy3dRtxu11xKwSe2</a><br>
Please: do not like / do not share / do not comment on this post<br>
<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.xxxxx2017.fr/">https://www.xxxxx2017.fr/</a><br>
<br>
</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The letters <em>XXXXX</em> were replaced in each of the 5 messages by the name of each candidate (example: François Fillon and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.fillon2017.fr/">www.fillon2017.fr</a>). A specific order of publication was assigned in advance so that the messages of support for each candidate were published equally often (6 times) in 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th, and 5th position across the 30 accounts used for the experiment. The contacts of each experimenter agreeing to fill out the Google questionnaire (see <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://goo.gl/forms/uGy3dRtxu11xKwSe2">here</a>) were then asked to report several pieces of information:</p>
<p>1°) which candidate appears first in your Facebook feed?</p>
<p>2°) which candidate do you plan to vote for?</p>
<p>3°) which candidate do you think your contacts will mostly vote for?</p>
<p>4°) have you ever relayed negative information against certain candidates?</p>
<p>5°) do you think Facebook is politically neutral?</p>
<p>6°) do you agree that on Facebook, we primarily see content that we like?</p>
<p>7°) in what order do the 5 candidates appear on your Facebook news feed?</p>
<p>NB: questions 2-7 were optional.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/design_bullesdefiltres.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="635"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 1. Example of referencing performed by the Facebook algorithm. Using the provided link, participants were invited to report the apparent order of the messages of support for each candidate in their news feed. By comparing this information with the chronological order of publication assigned to each of the 30 experimenters, it is possible to assess how the FB algorithm processes our political positions.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Over a one-month period (from February 28 to March 26), 737 responses were collected on the social network. Although the results of this study provide unique and sometimes unexpected insights, they must be approached with some caution for several reasons: the tested sample is not representative of the French population (overrepresentation of young, educated, left-leaning participants) and certain factors were not strictly controlled (spontaneous reactions to posts, number of responses per participant, number of responses per account, etc.). Moreover, this is not a scientific study in the strict sense: its methodology has not been evaluated by any research committee and the author of the study (namely, me) is not a specialist in social network analysis.</p>
<p>Nevertheless, it is worth noting that polling institutes are also far from meeting standard scientific criteria and they almost never release the raw data collected, hence <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.franceculture.fr/politique/sondages-faut-il-changer-de-methode">the proliferation of criticisms against them</a>. On the contrary, the methodology of this study, the raw data, and the scripts used for analysis are fully available online (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4815049.v1">here</a>), which should notably allow for the replication and refinement of the experiment, or to verify the reported conclusions. These findings prompt reflection on the role played by Facebook in presidential elections and show the usefulness (even necessity) of studying the social network to better account for (and possibly limit) its impact on the democratic process in France.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/intentions_de_vote.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="607"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 2. Political orientation of participants in this study. This sample of 737 participants is largely polarized to the left, which restricts the generality of the results reported.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As long as Facebook refuses to allow its users and public authorities to audit its <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.lemonde.fr/pixels/article/2014/07/01/comment-fonctionne-l-algorithme-de-facebook_4448781_4408996.html">algorithms</a> and its use of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.lemonde.fr/pixels/article/2016/02/09/donnees-personnelles-le-virulent-requisitoire-de-la-cnil-contre-facebook_4861621_4408996.html">personal information</a>, this approach will remain necessary.</p>
</section>
<section id="filter-bubbles-in-the-context-of-french-presidential-elections" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="filter-bubbles-in-the-context-of-french-presidential-elections">Filter Bubbles in the Context of French Presidential Elections</h3>
<p>Discussed and theorized for several years, particularly under the impulse of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.ted.com/talks/eli_pariser_beware_online_filter_bubbles?utm_source=tedcomshare&amp;utm_medium=referral&amp;utm_campaign=tedspread">Eli Pariser</a>, the problem of filter bubbles is related to the fact that the social network constantly personalizes our experience to show us content with which we are already in agreement or about which we have a prior interest. In an interview granted to <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://techland.time.com/2011/05/16/5-questions-with-eli-pariser-author-of-the-filter-bubble/">Time</a>, Eli Pariser indicated that on Facebook, “you indoctrinate yourself with your own opinions. You don’t realize that what you’re seeing is just a part of the picture. And this has consequences for democracy: to be a good citizen, you need to be able to put yourself in the shoes of others and have an overview. If everything you see is rooted in your own identity, it becomes difficult, if not impossible.”</p>
<p>The phenomenon must be distinguished from sociological confinement which stems from the fact (also very important) that we select our Facebook contacts based on pre-existing affinities, who in turn select their contacts in this way. For example, in this study, the very low number of participants declaring their intention to vote for François Fillon (10% of the expressed intentions) or Marine Le Pen (2% of the expressed intentions) undoubtedly reflects my own sociocultural confinement and the “social distance” that typically separates me from these voters (Figure 2). However, while most of us are aware of our sociological confinement, the filter bubbles generated by Facebook’s algorithms have a more pernicious influence, as they result from implicit (and largely unknown) control over the content we are exposed to.</p>
<p>In the data collected here, Facebook, for example, modified the real order of messages posted in 92% of cases, which “allowed” more than 30% (182) of the 595 individuals who expressed their voting intention to see their preferred candidate appear first in their news feed. Statistically, such a proportion is almost impossible to occur by chance, indicating that Facebook is indeed able to predict, to some extent, for which candidate we will vote, and that it uses this information to choose the content to which we are exposed.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/images/caa776294c3b77e67f2017f83a3cd007.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="817"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 3. Candidate appearing first in the news feed of participants according to their voting intention. The data are normalized so that the sum of each column equals 100, which means that the color code corresponds to the probability that a given candidate will appear first, given the voting intention of the participants. For example, the yellow box at the bottom right indicates that Marine Le Pen is seen first in more than 50% of cases by her potential voters.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>If we break down the analysis candidate by candidate (Figure 3), we observe that the effect is particularly true for Marine Le Pen (displayed first on the news feed of 54.5% of her potential voters), for Emmanuel Macron (first on the news feed of 38% of his potential voters) and, to a lesser extent, for Jean-Luc Mélenchon (34.4%) and François Fillon (28.8%). Only Benoît Hamon achieves a result opposite to the general trend, since only 17.8% of his potential voters saw him first in their news feed: the figure above indicates that Hamon’s voters actually tend to see positions in favor of Mélenchon or Macron first, which may seem logical given the delay taken by his campaign compared to these two candidates.</p>
</section>
<section id="filter-bubbles-and-useful-voting" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="filter-bubbles-and-useful-voting">“Filter Bubbles” and Useful Voting</h3>
<p>Thus, the existence of filter bubbles implies that we tend to see positions and content that reinforce us in our convictions. They therefore have a particularly problematic consequence in the specific context of French presidential elections: they probably reinforce the well-oiled mechanism of “useful voting” so <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.monde-diplomatique.fr/2017/04/HALIMI/57398">often criticized</a>. Indeed, useful voting is essentially a strategic vote consisting of voting for the candidate whom we believe has the most chances of winning against a given opponent. It therefore largely depends on a bet on the voting intentions of the social group as a whole.</p>
<p>Everyone knows that Emmanuel Macron represents the “useful vote” candidate today. Therefore, if the people who plan to vote for him are primarily exposed to positions favorable to this candidate on Facebook - to the detriment of statements (or shared content) in favor of other candidates - it is clear that this can only reinforce them in their strategy. To see if the phenomenon of filter bubbles could influence the perception of voting intentions within the social group, I crossed personal voting intentions (question 2) with the estimation of the majority vote within the social group (question 3). The results of this analysis, reported in Figure 4 below, are particularly striking:</p>
<p>- Potential voters of Mélenchon or Hamon generally consider that their entourage will vote mostly for Mélenchon (47% and 28%, respectively), for Hamon (25% and 37%) or for Macron (26% and 33%).<br>
- Potential voters of Fillon generally consider that their entourage will vote mostly for Fillon (52%) or for Macron (41%).<br>
- Potential voters of Le Pen generally consider that their entourage will vote mostly for Le Pen (36%), Fillon (27%) or Macron (36%)<br>
- Finally, potential voters of Macron consider that their entourage will vote for Macron in 65% of cases, a record in this regard. Fillon is, among these voters, the second candidate considered most often majority within the social group, but this happens only in 13% of cases!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/images/53021bc0717e92179e7e27e638302394-1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 4. Perceived majority on Facebook according to voting intentions. The data are normalized so that the sum of each rank equals 100, which means that the color code corresponds to the probability that a candidate is considered majority in the social group, given the voting intention of the participants. For example, the yellow box in the center means that 65% of potential voters of Emmanuel Macron consider that Emmanuel Macron will be majority among their Facebook contacts.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Two hypotheses are possible to explain this last observation: either the potential voters of Emmanuel Macron correctly assess the majority vote of their social group, or they suffer from a distortion that leads them to imagine Macron more majority than he really is. The data collected cannot definitively decide, even if the distribution of collected voting intentions (see Figure 2) suggests that the different social groups tested are not so favorable to Emmanuel Macron, and therefore that the second hypothesis has a chance of being valid. However, if the first hypothesis were valid, it would mean that potential voters of Macron are locked in a somewhat more hermetic sociocultural bubble than the others, which is not necessarily reassuring either… That being said, it must be said that the lack of data available for Marine Le Pen makes comparison with this candidate uncertain and that the overall results of the analysis could vary if the experiment were replicated in another social environment.</p>
<p>Finally, if it is important to emphasize the fact that potential voters of Emmanuel Macron suffer from a more intense filter-bubble effect than other voters, it is also because this result contrasts with their assessment of the social network. Thus, they paradoxically seem less in agreement (6.4) than the voters of Hamon (7.3) or Mélenchon (7.1) to say that “On Facebook, we tend to see primarily the posts of contacts sharing our ideas” (from 1, not at all, to 10 completely agree; Figure 5, right). Similarly, to the question “Do you trust the political neutrality of Facebook?” (from 1, not at all, to 10, completely trust), they obtain an average score of 4.5; the difference with the potential voters of Hamon (3.4) or Mélenchon (3.1) being statistically significant (Figure 5, left).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/images/a6a8135f9c2dea2247d346081ba184b3.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 5. Perception of Facebook according to voting intentions in the presidential elections. Overall, the results indicate a certain mistrust regarding the political neutrality of Facebook (majority of responses below 5 on the left graph) and they confirm that the participants in the study, mostly young, are aware that Facebook tends to create ‘filter bubbles’ (majority of responses above 5 on the right graph). Surprisingly, potential voters of Emmanuel Macron are less negative about Facebook than voters oriented more to the left.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="sensitive-issue-and-slippery-slope-does-facebook-favor-certain-candidates" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="sensitive-issue-and-slippery-slope-does-facebook-favor-certain-candidates">Sensitive Issue and Slippery Slope: Does Facebook Favor Certain Candidates?</h3>
<p>Technically, the data collected during this experiment also allow us to determine whether Facebook favors certain candidates over others. To avoid some exploiting the data posted online by taking it out of context, I report below a few analyses suggesting that Emmanuel Macron might be favored by the algorithms of the social network, which perhaps explains why the phenomenon of “filter bubbles” described above appears more marked for this candidate. But, it is good to take into account this advantage (especially when one belongs to a social environment similar to that of the present study), I must immediately caution the reader against any conspiracy theory interpretation that would consist of thinking that these analyses reveal a deliberate manipulation by Mark Zuckerberg! I explain why a little further down.</p>
<p>The first clue suggesting that Emmanuel Macron is favored compared to other candidates comes from the comparison between the proportion of participants who saw each candidate in the first position in their news feed and the proportion of participants who should have seen this candidate first if the chronological order were respected. Indeed, Emmanuel Macron is the candidate for whom this difference is the most favorable, whether one uses all the available data (+9%, against +5% for Mélenchon and -11% for Fillon) or systematically excludes from the analysis the responses where he was the favorite candidate of the participant considered (+5% against +2% for Le Pen and -12% for Fillon).</p>
<p>Then, if we examine the probability that each candidate is presented first in the news feed, knowing that he was actually first (according to the chronological order; Figure 6, left), or the same probability, knowing that he should have been last (still according to the chronological order; Figure 6, right), we again notice a fairly clear advantage in favor of Emmanuel Macron:</p>
<p>- When he is actually first according to the chronological order of publication, Macron is indeed seen first in the news feed in 45% of cases. By comparison, Le Pen (second on this scale) is actually first only in 30% of cases where she should be first and this proportion drops to 15% for JLM (last on this scale).</p>
<p>- When he should have been last (according to the chronological order), Macron still appears first in 53% of cases. By comparison, Le Pen (again second on this scale) appears first in 40% of cases where she should be last and this proportion drops to 4% for Fillon (last on this scale).</p>
<p>Looking more closely at the graphs that synthesize these data, we notice two other interesting trends. Firstly, Marine Le Pen often substitutes for Jean-Luc Mélenchon when he should appear first (33% of cases) - and vice versa (in 31% of cases). Secondly, Jean-Luc Mélenchon often substitutes for Benoît Hamon when the latter should appear first (37% of cases). These substitutions likely correspond to the association of these different candidates in press articles relayed on the social network, since we know that many journalists like to bring together Jean-Luc Mélenchon and Marine Le Pen on the one hand, and that the question of the rapprochement between Hamon and Mélenchon has occupied a lot of media space in recent months on the other hand.</p>
<p>The third and last clue allowing to highlight the favorable referencing of Emmanuel Macron comes from the analysis of a subset of the data, focused on the situation where the candidates considered are initially positioned in the 3rd position (i.e., central) in the chronological order of publication (Figure 7 below). By allowing the simultaneous visualization of upward and downward trends based on a well-defined situation, this analysis shows that Macron is raised in 50% of cases to the first or second place (against 32% for Hamon, second, and 21% for Le Pen, last), and in 41% of cases to the first place (against 10% for Fillon, second and 4% for Le Pen, last). With Hamon (65%), Emmanuel Macron (64%) is thus the candidate who has the highest chance of maintaining or moving up in the referencing of Facebook when starting from a chronologically intermediate position.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/images/94b419aa5cecc2f4157d408db99fe9e7.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="655"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 7. Rank observed in the news feed when each candidate is published in 3rd position according to the chronological order of publication.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>As I wrote above, we should not infer from these data that Emmanuel Macron is intentionally favored by the company, nor that the results obtained would be replicable in any social environment. It is for example possible that Emmanuel Macron is favored simply because he appears more often in the media or because he generally elicits fewer negative comments than more polarized candidates - whether on the left or the right. Even though we cannot strictly exclude this hypothesis, it therefore remains highly improbable that Facebook intentionally favors one candidate over others: it is more likely a “phenomenon emerging” linked to the functioning of the referencing algorithms.</p>
<p>Certainly, academic research on Facebook exists and allows for fascinating results from a sociological point of view. Some are even sponsored by the company itself like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://cn.cnstudiodev.com/uploads/document_attachment/attachment/681/science_facebook_filter_bubble_may2015.pdf">this study conducted on 11 million Americans</a> published in the journal Science in 2015 (which was obviously reassuring about the phenomenon of filter bubbles). However, the control over the diffusion of content exercised by the company has <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://qz.com/936503/facebooks-new-method-of-fighting-fake-news-is-making-it-hard-for-people-to-post-a-false-story-about-irish-slaves/">recently intensified with the debate on “fake news”</a> and the slowness of academic research is in any case little compatible with political or media timelines. While waiting for Facebook to offer more guarantees regarding its functioning (intentional or accidental) and given the precedent represented by its successful attempt at <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/jun/29/facebook-users-emotions-news-feeds">“emotional control”</a> - published in 2013 in the journal <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.pnas.org/content/111/24/8788.full">PNAS</a>, the creation of a citizen observatory that would conduct on a larger scale experiments similar to the one described here would therefore be very useful.</p>
</section>
<section id="how-does-facebook-know-who-you-will-vote-for" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="how-does-facebook-know-who-you-will-vote-for">How Does Facebook Know Who You Will Vote For?</h3>
<p>Much has been written about how Facebook processes our personal information to better predict our preferences (political or otherwise) and expose us to content that generates revenue. During this experiment, I noticed that some people thought they were immune to Facebook’s political classifications because they do not share and do not react to the content that is distributed there. Therefore, for these people, the idea that a filter bubble could nevertheless bias their perception of political news often seems absurd.</p>
<p>However, a number of factors such as age, gender, the composition of the circle of contacts, the content viewed, or the type of pages followed allow Facebook to profile these users more as spectators than actors. Moreover, its algorithms can also rely on indirect information: in the data described here, it appears for example that the use of Facebook during the day differs significantly depending on the left-right divide (Figure 8): compared to users on the left, right-wing users show a more marked peak of activity between 5 pm and 9 pm, so that the simple distribution of our activity on Facebook already says something about our political orientation. By the way, and to conclude, this kind of information also allows Facebook and the companies that exploit its data to have a fairly precise idea of our <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rythme_circadien">circadian rhythm</a> (or “biological clock”), which opens a door to our lifestyle…</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/images/245c04b11d1399338f31551c8112fa96-2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="635"></p>
<figcaption>Figure 8. Use of Facebook during the day depending on the political left-right divide. The grayed area corresponds to the time slot 5 pm-9 pm over which the difference between the two curves is significant.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="going-further" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="going-further">Going Further</h3>
<p>- The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://dataselfie.it/#/">Data Selfie</a> extension for Chrome allows you to visualize in real-time the data that Facebook collects about us.</p>
<p>- The mechanism of referencing on Facebook is evolving rapidly at the moment, notably under the impetus of the artificial intelligence department of Facebook led by the Frenchman Yann LeCun (a researcher at the origin of the so-called “deep-learning” revolution) who would even, eventually, like each user’s experience to be controlled by a <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://fortune.com/facebook-machine-learning/">dedicated artificial intelligence</a>. Thus, the excellent courses given by Yann LeCun last year at the Collège de France (available online <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.college-de-france.fr/site/yann-lecun/course-2015-2016.htm">here</a>) give a very good idea of the stakes of artificial intelligence and the type of algorithms used by Facebook today.</p>
<p>- The wonderful tool <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://presidentielle2017.iscpif.fr/">Politoscope</a> put online this Monday, April 3, by researchers from the Institut des Systèmes Complexes de Paris-Ile-de-France allows us to visualize with a very high degree of precision different social dynamics related to the presidential campaign on Twitter.</p>
<p>- Entitled <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.dailymotion.com/video/x55sim8">“Should We Burn Facebook?”</a>, the interview given to Mediapart by Antonio Casilli, researcher and lecturer at Telecom ParisTech links the business model of Facebook and the principle of filter bubbles and shows the importance of the question for democratic societies.</p>
<p>- As fascinating as it is terrifying, the interactive documentary <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://donottrack-doc.com/fr/">Do-Not-Track</a> dissects the mechanics of individual profiling on the internet (which extends to our personalities, our addictions, our anxieties, our bank accounts, etc.) and shows that the data extracted from social networks are increasingly used by private companies (for example, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2016/nov/02/admiral-to-price-car-insurance-based-on-facebook-posts">insurance companies</a>) and by public authorities (for example, to profile <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.theverge.com/2017/3/10/14887818/dhs-ice-customs-social-media-screening-report-inspector-general">immigrants</a> or to <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/https://www.theguardian.com/environment/earth-insight/2014/jun/12/pentagon-mass-civil-breakdown?CMP=twt_gu">anticipate or counter social protest movements</a>).</p>
<p>- Finally, not everyone shares the idea that filter bubbles are so detrimental to the democratic debate: see for example <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://imagesociale.fr/3666">the reflection of André Gunther</a> the day after the election of Donald Trump or <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://www.vox.com/policy-and-politics/2017/3/29/14983026/social-media-polarization-study-nber">this recent study</a> suggesting that filter bubbles contribute less than one might think to polarizing the political space (which is, however, not the argument of the present post).</p>
<hr>
<p>Thank you to all the experimental assistants and participants who made this study possible!</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20201021022118/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2017/04/04/presidentielles-et-bulles-de-filtres-le-referencement-politique-de-facebook-passe-au-crible/"><strong>Original article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>citizen science</category>
  <category>medias</category>
  <category>social network</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/filterbubbles/bleu_blanc_rouge.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Reflecting on Defiance with Henri Laborit</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/laboritrebellion/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>It must be acknowledged that the concept of submission occupies an increasingly prominent place in the cultural and social landscape of our country. So much so that its rejection has become the rallying cry of a political force mobilizing several million citizens.</p>
<p>Although it seems unlikely that these ideas will reach the second round of the presidential election in the current state of affairs, this does not exempt us from reflecting on what submission and its refusal mean. On one hand, the game is not yet lost, as some alliances remain possible and many undecided voters can still be convinced. On the other hand, the issue of submission will remain on the agenda as long as the concentration of power and capital prevails over social goods, democracy, and the entire planet.</p>
<p>The demand to do better and think better remains. If we want the issue to gain full scope and become a central concern for a majority of voters, we need to give more substance and depth to this concept that has haunted our consciousness since Etienne de la Boétie’s <em>Discourse on Voluntary Servitude</em> (1548).</p>
<p>We must free ourselves from systems that address submission exclusively from a sociological or economic perspective, as these define counterproductive and sometimes unfounded fault lines that weaken the cause they seek to promote. To be convinced, one only needs to observe that a significant portion of the country’s intellectual elite—often of bourgeois origin—shares the analysis of the “Insoumis,” while half of the working class supports a family of millionaire and authoritarian landlords.</p>
<p>Therefore, it is not on the sociological or economic level that the refusal of submission will become universal and redefine the system in which we live, but on the psychological level and—by extension—the biological level.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/laboritrebellion/images/paste-1.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="338"></p>
<figcaption>Undated portrait of the French surgeon, biologist, and writer Henri Laborit (1914-1995). In 1952, he discovered a class of drugs used in surgery and psychiatry, neuroleptics based on chlorpromazine. It was in his efforts to improve anesthesia techniques in surgery that he discovered this product, which is now widely used in psychiatric clinics. AFP</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="the-figure-of-the-committed-biologist" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-figure-of-the-committed-biologist">The Figure of the Committed Biologist</h3>
<p>Surgeon and neurobiologist Henri Laborit was among the most famous French scientists of the second half of the 20th century, having discovered, among other things, the first neuroleptics (molecules used in the treatment of schizophrenia). But he was also a great theorist of social hierarchies, from their evolutionary origin to their neurobiological instantiation, including their anthropological study and cinematic representation (in <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/https://youtu.be/FQcC-VB_W-s"><em>Mon Oncle d’Amérique</em></a>, for which he won the Palme d’Or in 1980 alongside Alain Resnais).</p>
<p>Laborit saw dominance and submission as two sides of the same scourge that he fought to the end with the tools at his disposal. It is even said that his aversion to the flattery and academic bowing necessary to gain the favor of the Parisian medical intelligentsia deprived him of the Nobel Prize (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/http://www.elogedelasuite.net/wp-content/uploads/2015/02/Le-docteur-Henri-Laborit-l%C3%A9nergie-et-lintelligence-du-off.pdf">source</a>, see also the obituary published by <em>Libération</em> on <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/http://www.liberation.fr/sciences/1995/05/20/henri-laborit-un-savant-prend-la-fuite_131730">May 20, 1995</a>).</p>
<p>Despite strong involvement in public debate, his independence of mind kept him away from any political party: Henri Laborit harshly criticized both capitalism and communism. He argued that building a new ecological and social path would depend on our ability to integrate—into political construction—the discoveries from the “biology of behavior” (which we would call today cognitive neuroscience), cybernetics, and complexity sciences, of which he was one of the pioneers.</p>
<p>Due to the richness and multiple levels of description that distinguish Henri Laborit’s thought, it is very difficult to synthesize it. Furthermore, as some of my works aim to deepen, test, and modernize several hypotheses and theories that pervade his work, I would always be tempted to substitute my thinking for his, at the risk of distorting both his legacy and my own understanding of the problem.</p>
<p>Therefore, I propose that the reader remember Henri Laborit or become familiar with him through a series of quotes from his most widely circulated book: <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (1976). These fragments are organized into eight major themes. More relevant than ever, I hope they will provide food for thought, both for those who defend defiance and for those who believe they can do without it.</p>
</section>
<section id="submission-as-a-means-of-domination" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="submission-as-a-means-of-domination"><strong>Submission as a Means of Domination</strong></h3>
<p>“Culture of an era represents […] the rules to which an individual must submit […] to rise in hierarchies and achieve dominance.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p107, Folio essais).</p>
<p>“Every little French child is told they can hope to one day become president of the Republic. But they forget to add: if they respect the rules of the game, the value judgments institutionalized by the bourgeoisie, particularly private property, including that of the means of production.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p109, ibid.)</p>
<p>“Thus, we will see individuals who are particularly effective […] on a technical level and perfectly obtuse on a political level, as they are sufficiently satisfied with their dominance not to seek to lucidly see its causes, meaning, or especially to question it.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p143).</p>
<p>“A prisoner inside the walls of his prison is free to dream, and a CEO, apparently free to move, will only do so by obeying the alienating myth of property, profitability, and production. The pursuit of dominance leads us to the most primitive mechanisms of our central nervous system as inexorably as police handcuffs.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p160)</p>
</section>
<section id="submission-as-existential-diversion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="submission-as-existential-diversion"><strong>Submission as Existential Diversion</strong></h3>
<p>“This anxiety that grips every human being by the throat as soon as they become aware of being, and that does not leave them until death, contemporary societies make a constant effort to obscure because it hinders their production-oriented goal. One might even wonder if it is not an important factor in the establishment of hierarchies. When one is preoccupied with social promotion, one is less concerned with the meaning of one’s own existence and becomes more efficient in a production process. One might wonder if the one who succeeds best in such a process, whose hierarchical elevation is the most assured, is not ultimately the least human, the least conscious, the most blind, I would be tempted to say the least ‘intelligent,’ the most automated, the most satisfied, the most gratified by their dominance, the least anxious, the true ‘happy fool.’” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p201).</p>
<p>“It should be noted that while hierarchical systems are sources of conflict and anxiety, they are also a source of security. The creation of conceptual and behavioral automatisms of sociocultural origin allows the concealment of existential anxiety by providing simple explanatory frameworks, responsible and reassuring leaders, and most often smaller individuals to patronize to satisfy congenital narcissism. Unfortunately, it stifles all creativity by punishing any project that does not conform to the value system imposed by the dominants.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p71).</p>
</section>
<section id="the-figure-of-the-submissive-intellectual" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-figure-of-the-submissive-intellectual"><strong>The Figure of the Submissive Intellectual</strong></h3>
<p>“The one commonly referred to as the intellectual, especially specialized in a certain technique, would benefit, for some, from power. Indeed, one can admit that if they prove to be an effective propagandist of the value judgments that constitute the framework of the society in which they live, they will be gratified accordingly: means of work, access to means of disseminating the commonplaces they express, ‘honors,’ academic satisfactions will be granted to them for having played this role of honest man, true humanist who has shown so much elevation of spirit. Indeed, the elevation of spirit is only achievable, as we know, within the dominant ideology, the one that ensures the solidity of the hierarchical structures in place.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p201).</p>
</section>
<section id="consumption-as-submission" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="consumption-as-submission"><strong>Consumption as Submission</strong></h3>
<p>“All advertising is based on this need to make known to create the need. One cannot desire what one is unaware of. Conversely, one can desire what another possesses and what one does not possess. Especially if the possession of the object allows one to position oneself in a hierarchical order and participates in establishing dominance.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p104).</p>
<p>“As long as value hierarchies persist and are established on property through the possession of specialized information acquired by manual or conceptual learning, the dominated will seek to conquer a false power that is consumption. However, consumption has no end, and real equality of chances and power can never be established through consumption. The real power that the dominated demands is less that of consuming than that of participating in decision-making. For this, it is generalized information and not just specialized information that they must acquire.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p156).</p>
</section>
<section id="from-class-struggle-to-functional-classes" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="from-class-struggle-to-functional-classes"><strong>From Class Struggle to Functional Classes</strong></h3>
<p>“On the political level, that is to say, in terms of the meaning of each person’s work integrated into a whole and the purpose of this whole in the higher complexity ensembles that encompass it, a highly specialized engineer often has no more knowledge than a specialized worker, although different, as they are dictated by value judgments and prejudices necessary to maintain their hierarchical dominance.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p119)</p>
<p>“In a living organism, functional specialization, which in a social organism is equivalent to professional specialization, is accompanied by no particular value and […] it provides no possibility of acting apart from the organic whole.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p120)</p>
<p>“These functional classes have nothing to do with the hierarchical classes of ‘class struggle.’ But as we have seen, by introducing the notion of information in human sociology, hierarchical scales are so progressive that it is impossible to know at what point one leaves the proletariat to enter the bourgeoisie, impossible to know on what criteria an individual can be classified in one class or another, except for a state of mind or party affiliation. One might wonder if the notion of class as it was understood and experienced at the beginning of the century still has any reality other than affective.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p154).</p>
</section>
<section id="dominating-others-dominating-nature" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dominating-others-dominating-nature"><strong>Dominating Others, Dominating Nature</strong></h3>
<p>“The benefit of increased industrial production is often only a short-term benefit and a long-term tragedy […]. Other consequences of growth have also been cited: depletion of energy resources, accelerated accumulation of non-recyclable waste in the great cycles of matter. Thus, the pursuit of dominance through the myth of consumer goods production, also requiring large human concentrations within modern megacities, polluting to the benefit mainly of the dominants (since it is the pursuit of dominance that is the motivation) collective goods such as air, water, built space, and sound space, […] today constitutes a real threat to the entire human species.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p156).</p>
<p>“The problem is therefore to understand how the myth of growth for growth’s sake, not only for the satisfaction of fundamental needs, has been established, obscuring motivations to such an extent that it is taken as the basis of social behavior in industrialized countries, and can today be defended as an end in itself, as the very purpose of the human species, enveloped in affective-mystical notions such as happiness, needs, progress, the domination of man over mother nature, if not the genius of the white race, or a particular ideological regime.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p105).</p>
</section>
<section id="the-insufficiency-of-sociological-defiance" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-insufficiency-of-sociological-defiance"><strong>The Insufficiency of Sociological Defiance</strong></h3>
<p>“Believing that one has gotten rid of bourgeois individualism because one expresses oneself in the protective shadow of social classes and their struggles, seemingly acting against profit, the exploitation of man by man, the powers of money, established powers, is to show perfect ignorance of what motivates, directs, orients human actions and above all what motivates, directs, and orients our own judgments, our own actions. This does not mean that one should not express oneself and act in this way, but it means that it is useful to know that behind a supposedly altruistic and generous discourse, there are hidden instinctual motivations, unfulfilled desires for dominance, cultural learnings, a submission rewarded by their prohibitions, or an ineffective revolt against the alienation of our gratifying acts to the social order, a search for narcissistic satisfactions, etc. So that when a community of interests allows a human group to overthrow the established power one day, a competitive struggle for dominance is immediately born within the new power, a new hierarchical system appears and institutionalizes itself. The cycle begins again.” <em>L’Éloge de la fuite</em></p>
</section>
<section id="the-importance-of-transmitting-neuroscientific-knowledge" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-importance-of-transmitting-neuroscientific-knowledge"><strong>The Importance of Transmitting Neuroscientific Knowledge</strong></h3>
<p>“It is […] through an increasing knowledge of the structures of the world around him that [man] has been able to structure it in return to the best of his thinking. At least until a recent era. But the ignorance he still has of the functional structure of his nervous system has prevented him from effectively acting on himself and on his relations with his contemporaries.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p135)</p>
<p>“When the laws of gravitation were known, man was able to go to the moon. By doing so, he did not free himself from the laws of gravitation, but he was able to use them to his advantage.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p161).</p>
<p>“Ignorance of the biophysiological bases of behaviors means that any benefactor of the people, if they do more than just talk in their name and engage in action, will quickly act for themselves or for the concepts they manipulate, which are generally not those of the common people.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p171)</p>
<p>“Perhaps it is time to tell them […] that there is also an emerging science whose foundations urgently need to be disseminated, as arithmetic foundations were disseminated, indispensable to mercantile civilizations to ensure their accounting, and that this science is that of the living world.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p100)</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h3>
<p>Henri Laborit did not hesitate to call revolutionary the idea that the neuroscientific analytical framework—once integrated and understood by a majority of citizens—would not only allow the construction of more effective institutions but also a society more resilient against the drifts associated with the exercise of power. On a smaller scale, he believed that knowledge of human motivations and (cognitive) biases should also enrich our social interactions, liberate our inner lives, and increase our capacity to undertake together.</p>
<p>In this regard, it is exciting to observe the proliferation of initiatives aimed at disseminating knowledge in (neuro)cognitive and social sciences. These include events like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/https://www.semaineducerveau.fr/2017/">Brain Week</a> (March 13-17, 2017) and the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/http://forumsciencescognitives.com/">Cognitive Sciences Forum</a> (April 29, 2017), very active associations like <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/http://coginnov.org/">Cog’Innov</a>, collective blogs such as <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/http://www.cortex-mag.net/">Cortex Mag</a>, but also numerous individual blogs run by researchers, journalists, or ordinary citizens passionate about the human mind.</p>
<p>As the phenomenon is young, the connection with more politically oriented citizen initiatives has not yet occurred. But there is no doubt that the movement will continue to expand and that neuroscience will occupy an increasingly important place in future public debates. Beyond understanding (and disarming) the mechanisms responsible for the perpetual recurrence and reinforcement of dominance and inequalities, many other issues bring us back to it: new forms of addiction, aging population, cognitive enhancement, brain-computer interfaces, artificial intelligence, etc.</p>
<p>That said, this tribute to Henri Laborit would not be complete without a warning against any dogmatic use of neuroscientific knowledge. Indeed, he always decried blind adherence to grand discourses and definitive utopias, in which he saw a promise of intellectual and social stagnation. In all his works, the reader is invited to think beyond ideologies and commonplaces and to use existing frameworks (including his own) only to enrich new analyses and define new objectives adapted to present contingencies.</p>
<p>“When the attraction of myths, of the irrational, is not sufficient to gain its adherence, contemporary youth ‘satisfies’ itself by using known frameworks, the Marxist framework or the psychoanalytic framework which seem to provide a coherent answer to the fundamental questions posed by any conscious man at the end of the 20th century. These frameworks unfortunately refuse permission to seek beyond them and further. They themselves are indeed at the base of individual and group hierarchies.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p99)</p>
<p>“The danger of a framework, whatever its temporary effectiveness, is to facilitate conceptual sclerosis, as Aristotle’s framework before that of Marx or Freud’s framework froze millions of men in an incomplete conception of facts.” <em>La nouvelle grille</em> (p157).</p>
<p>Let us therefore be careful not to repeat the same mistake with the “new frameworks” from neuroscience research. Even if they allow us to explain the world’s evolutions better than before, they will never replace the effort of imagination and intellectual cooperation on which our common future depends.</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200923024131/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2017/02/06/penser-linsoumission-avec-henri-laborit/"><strong>Original Article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/laboritrebellion/dore_laborit.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="667"></p>
<figcaption>Portrait of Henri Laborit by <a href="https://www.antoinedore.com/">Antoine Doré</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>inequalities</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>books</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/laboritrebellion/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/laboritrebellion/dore_laborit.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Is Trump’s Victory a Defeat for Intelligence?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/trump/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Entitled “Cognitive Ability and Authoritarianism: Understanding Support for Trump and Clinton,” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200831015721/http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0191886916310911">the article</a> by Becky Choma and Yaniv Hanoch describes the complex relationship between cognitive ability and support for the new American president, Donald Trump.</p>
<p>Specifically, the researchers invited 400 American voters to take an IQ test (very abbreviated, hence the vague term “cognitive ability”) and a series of questionnaires. Among these were questions about voting intentions and pro-Trump opinions, as well as two personality scales known as SDO (Social Dominance Orientation) and RWA (Right-Wing Authoritarianism).</p>
<p>The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200831015721/https://blogs.mediapart.fr/horslesmurs/blog/110816/inegalites-sociales-le-profil-cognitif-de-ceux-qui-s-en-foutent">SDO</a> is frequently used in psychology to assess the tendency to legitimize hierarchical relationships within societies (e.g., men-women, whites-minorities, etc.). The <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200831015721/http://quebec.huffingtonpost.ca/Bruno%20Mass%C3%A9/psychologie-conservateurs-canada_b_3279747.html">RWA</a> is used to evaluate the tendency to desire an authoritarian, conservative government that upholds traditional, particularly religious, values.</p>
<section id="the-indirect-link-between-trumpism-and-intelligence" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-indirect-link-between-trumpism-and-intelligence">The Indirect Link Between Trumpism and Intelligence</h3>
<p>While the results indicate there is no <em>direct</em> link between intelligence and voting for Trump, they do highlight an <em>indirect</em> link.</p>
<p>A path analysis (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200831015721/http://leger360.com/admin/leger_a/fr_la7_pathanalysis.pdf">PDF</a>) revealed that lower cognitive ability is, on average, associated with a stronger legitimization of existing dominance relationships (SDO) and a stronger attraction to authoritarian and traditionalist policies (RWA). Since these two scales have a powerful impact on adherence to Trump’s theses (and more generally to <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200831015721/https://blogs.mediapart.fr/horslesmurs/blog/110816/inegalites-sociales-le-profil-cognitif-de-ceux-qui-s-en-foutent">conservative theses</a>), intelligence likely played an indirect role in the outcome of the American presidential election.</p>
<p>In summary, individuals with lower IQs were, on average, more likely to vote for Trump due to increased sensitivity to discourses that propose reinforcing the domination of certain social groups over others, based on religious or racial distinctions. It would have been interesting to know if these same voters also readily accept authority relationships based on intellectual or academic distinctions, but the researchers did not address this question.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/trump/mediation.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="744"></p>
<figcaption>Summary of the study published in the Journal of Personality and Individual Differences on 11/3/2016. Plus symbols (+) denote a positive association between variables, minus symbols (-) denote a negative association.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Obviously, since the study was conducted online and the evaluation of intelligence remains very rudimentary, its results should be interpreted with caution. Moreover, although statistically significant, the effect explains only a small portion of the variance in voting intentions (less than 5%). Finally, the mechanism linking intelligence and political opinions could be different in the United States and France.</p>
<p>That said, the researchers accounted for the influence of many other variables on the result, which is a strength. For example, their data show that being older or wealthier facilitates voting for Trump, while being more educated facilitates voting for Clinton, but accounting for these demographic factors does not change the main effect of the study: the indirect link “intelligence → SDO/RWA → vote Trump” remains.</p>
</section>
<section id="a-struggle-for-simplicity" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-struggle-for-simplicity">A Struggle for Simplicity</h3>
<p>Is Choma and Hanoch’s study relevant for countering the rise of far-right ideas in French society?</p>
<p>Perhaps. Indeed, if the difficulty in understanding the world we live in is the reason for communal retreat and authoritarian desire, it seems essential for the (true) left to clearly articulate its vision of the world and its project for the future. In other words, to simplify its message without falling into simplism and without betraying itself.</p>
<p>Some might argue that it is technically impossible to be simpler than the primary Manichaeism of a Trump or a Le Pen.</p>
<p>But this is not necessarily true. After all, far-right discourses rely on constructing a binary world distinguishing <em>them</em> and <em>us</em>, while internationalist left has always pursued the idea of a unitary world, that of <em>humanity</em>.</p>
<p>Putting this <em>human</em> at the forefront and showing the difficulty of establishing a sensible and non-arbitrary demarcation between <em>them</em> and <em>us</em> could ultimately shift the simplicity to the other side.</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200831015721/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2016/11/09/victoire-de-trump-une-defaite-de-lintelligence/"><strong>Original Article (Wayback Machine)</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>neuro89</category>
  <category>cognitive sciences</category>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>inequalities</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/trump/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2016 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/trump/trump.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>500,000 British Brains Scanned by MRI by 2022, and Then What?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Libération</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/biobank2022/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Each year, thousands of publications collectively deepen our understanding of the human brain and our ability to heal, influence, and alter it. These research efforts are essential to combat neurological and psychiatric diseases, whose prevalence increases as our life expectancy grows and our environment diverges from the one in which we evolved just a few thousand years ago. However, the benefits are not inherently linked to the knowledge produced by researchers. On the contrary, they entirely depend on how society as a whole decides to use it.</p>
<p>It is not the will of the researchers, but the vote of all citizens that will determine in which society this knowledge will find a function and the legitimate limits of its use. Personally, I am concerned about the use that will be made of my own work, both present and future. This is indeed why I am involved in the adventure of Hemisphère Gauche, as a way to escape a few hours a week from the austerity of the academic world to step into the chaotic but vital whirlwind of the real world.</p>
<section id="the-development-of-biobanks" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-development-of-biobanks">The Development of “Biobanks”</h3>
<p>To take just one example, a study published on September 19 in the prestigious journal <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200830155831/http://www.nature.com/neuro/journal/vaop/ncurrent/full/nn.4393.html">Nature Neuroscience</a> describes the methods and initial results of the monumental “UK Biobank” project, which aims to collect a complete set of psychological, biological, and genetic data on 500,000 inhabitants of the United Kingdom aged between 40 and 70 by 2022. Its stated goal is the development of tools to predict the risks of developing certain neurodegenerative diseases on an individual scale, thereby facilitating the creation of new treatments to prevent their occurrence.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/biobank2022/biobank.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="799"></p>
<figcaption>Figure showing different measures of brain connectivity (a-b) collected within the UK Biobank project, and their association with various variables of interest (c-d): health, cognition, lifestyle, etc.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Unfortunately, in an economy as deregulated as ours, we can fear that this same knowledge may also allow insurance companies, banks, and employers to assess these same vulnerabilities before establishing a contract with individuals, resulting in more unequal access to healthcare, housing, and employment. The upcoming advent of such practices – for example, including a brain imaging exam in the hiring process – is not science fiction, as there are researchers (albeit a very small minority) who recommend their implementation within a few years.</p>
<p>Willem Verbeke from the University of Rotterdam, for instance, supports the idea that a battery of neurobiological exams could detect at-risk profiles in advance before hiring individuals for important positions:</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<p>“If someone wanted to become the director of a company, I would probably want a scan of their brain first to be sure they do not have psychopathic or autistic tendencies.” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200830155831/https://www.nextnature.net/2009/02/brain-scan-replaces-job-interview-in-5-years/">source</a> (my translation)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In this specific case, good luck to Verbeke in detecting psychopathic tendencies by glancing at a candidate’s brain, because it will take neurosciences at least 20 years, if not more, to make such diagnostics. However, the problem is not so much practical as it is ethical. Other diseases, such as Parkinson’s, are much closer to being <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200830155831/http://brain.oxfordjournals.org/content/127/8/1693.short">anticipated</a>. And already, brain data can give a rough idea of an individual’s intelligence quotient, so much so that others imagine using it at the time of <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200830155831/http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/scientists-can-now-predict-how-intelligent-you-are-with-a-brain-scan-but-could-it-lead-to-a6693616.html">university</a> admissions… What will we decide the day these technologies are truly available?</p>
</section>
<section id="imagining-the-flip-side-without-undercutting-ourselves" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="imagining-the-flip-side-without-undercutting-ourselves">Imagining the Flip Side Without Undercutting Ourselves</h3>
<p>Furthermore, the “screening” of populations for profit is not the only potential misuse of knowledge generated by neuroscience. There are others, which I will address in the future, among them the commodification of brain modification techniques, neuromarketing, and the fallacious use of scientific conclusions for political ends (we notably remember comments by <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200830155831/http://www.lemonde.fr/societe/article/2007/04/11/tolle-chez-les-scientifiques-apres-les-propos-de-nicolas-sarkozy-sur-la-genetique_894367_3224.html">Nicolas Sarkozy on pedophilia and suicidal tendencies</a>).</p>
<p>It is obviously heart-breaking for researchers to communicate about these potential deviations, but it seems to me that a constructive dissemination of knowledge also involves warning against its less thrilling applications. Because we are best placed to imagine the benefits, as well as the risks, associated with the scientific advancements in which we participate.</p>
<p><a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200830155831/http://hemisphere-gauche.blogs.liberation.fr/2016/10/26/projet-biobank/">Original article (Wayback Archive)</a></p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>liberation</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>genetics</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/biobank2022/</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/biobank2022/brainwarhol.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Social Inequalities: The Cognitive Profile of Those Who Don’t Care.</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Mediapart</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/thosewhodontgiveaf/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>As anticipated in the government’s schedule, Euro 2016, the Olympics, and the August sun were enough to relegate social issues to the background. It is clear that idealists and the outraged have lost a battle. Nuit Debout may have fizzled out, but should we consider the occupations of public spaces and spring protests as another futile effort? The answer depends on our ability to learn and return stronger in the autumn, and to be more aware when it’s time to elect a new leader.</p>
<p>There is at least one thing this major social movement, punctuated by the physical violence of the CRS and the moral violence of the 49-3, has taught us: there exists in France a system of social domination so powerful and self-assured that its representatives no longer even pretend to care about democracy.</p>
<p>Anyone is free to believe that the most harmful person to our country is named Mohamed and drives refrigerated trucks, or that he is named Manuel and is driving France into the abyss. For an avoidable massacre on the Promenade des Anglais, how many avoidable deaths occur in the beds of our underfunded hospitals?</p>
<section id="unmasking" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="unmasking"><strong>Unmasking</strong></h2>
<p>From Juncker to Valls, including Hollande and Sarkozy, the indifference of the dominant political classes towards the inequalities generated by ultra-liberal logic is more evident than ever. These reforms, led by a socialist government elected to implement the opposite policy, prove that this indifference is not a matter of political color but is rooted in the very structures of the Fifth Republic.</p>
<p>Even the speeches of a brilliant polymath like Frédéric Lordon remain on the periphery of certain crucial questions. The will of the citizen is hindered by a structural problem, certainly, but before being implemented by institutions, any policy is first decided by individuals. Thus, to the institutional structures cherished by Lordon, we must add the psychological or cultural structures once dear to Foucault and Lévi-Strauss.</p>
<p>Since a politician like Manuel Valls’s policies clearly do not rely on popular will or what he forgot to learn in his <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://libertes.blog.lemonde.fr/2015/12/05/decheance-de-nationalite-le-precedent-de-vichy/">History degree</a>, they likely stem from personal motivations and influences that we need to better understand.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, as unique as he may be, the Prime Minister is just one embodiment of the malady that afflicts our society from the top. He is a product of his time—a highly successful one, but replaceable. Cut off his head, and a hundred more will grow. The problem lies not with the individuals themselves but with the system that shapes and selects them.</p>
<p>To inscribe the struggle for democracy and social justice in the long term, beyond football and weather contingencies, beyond the constant media noise, it is essential to understand the psychological dynamics of the dominant class.</p>
<p><em>“He who knows his enemy as he knows himself will not be defeated in a hundred battles. He who knows himself but not the enemy will win one and lose one. He who knows neither his enemy nor himself is always in danger.”</em> — Sun Tzu, The Art of War</p>
</section>
<section id="are-the-gauls-still-indomitable" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="are-the-gauls-still-indomitable"><strong>Are the Gauls still indomitable?</strong></h2>
<p>Social dominance is a phenomenon that emerges spontaneously through competition among individuals of the same species. This competition is inevitable when living conditions and resources deteriorate, and humans are certainly no exception. It is a natural principle that has always structured human societies and deeply shaped how our brains and bodies function. In humans, the thirst for dominance persists well beyond the satisfaction of biological needs, hence the ancient proverb “man is a wolf to man.”</p>
<p>However, dominance hierarchies are never irreversible. As Étienne de la Boétie wrote in his timeless <em>Discourse on Voluntary Servitude</em> nearly five centuries ago, they exist only as long as men tolerate being kept in subordination. Contemporary primatologists like Bernstein and Rowell echo this, considering that a dominance relationship is established only when an individual or group of individuals ceases to defend their rights or pursue their aspirations after being “defeated” by another individual or group.</p>
<p>In other words, the psychological dynamics at work in the middle and lower classes play an equally important role in maintaining the status quo we deplore. Although their symptoms differ, Manuel and Mohamed are together victims of the same alienating and deadly logic: that of dominance and subordination, which must be distinguished from other hierarchical constructions like prestige or leadership.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-desire-for-dominance-and-its-justification" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-desire-for-dominance-and-its-justification"><strong>The Desire for Dominance and Its Justification</strong></h2>
<p>Today, a professor at Harvard, <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://scholar.harvard.edu/sidanius/home">Jim Sidanius</a> initiated a resurgence of research on social dominance in humans in the early 2000s. In his most cited work, <em>Social Dominance: An Intergroup Theory of Social Hierarchy and Oppression,</em> he describes how human societies are structured around the problem of dominance—how the behaviors and beliefs of those who reinforce or seek to legitimize dominance interact with those who seek to combat and deconstruct it. His conclusions are partly based on the analysis of the SDO scale (Social Dominance Orientation), which measures the propensity to justify social inequalities and desire a stable hierarchical order. Respondents indicate their agreement (from 1, not at all, to 7, completely) with about fifteen statements such as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some people are simply inferior to others.</li>
<li>To get ahead in life, it is sometimes necessary to step on others.</li>
<li>The country would be better off if we cared less about social inequalities.</li>
<li>It is probably a good thing that certain groups are at the top and others are at the bottom.</li>
<li>Lower groups should stay in their place.</li>
</ul>
<p>Etc., etc. (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/3207711/Sidanius_SocialDominanceOrientation.pdf?sequence=">PDF</a>)</p>
<p>During my own research on social hierarchies and the brain (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://drive.google.com/file/d/0Bw7SZPk0IiJjQnJXc3FxcmpKWW8/view?usp=sharing">PDF</a>), I was stunned by the results of young French and Swiss students on this questionnaire and by the extremely high scores observed in some. My naivety took a hit, my optimism too, and this awareness led to many readings and reflections.</p>
<p>Historically, the SDO scale is akin to the ” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://www.cairn.info/revue-tumultes-2004-2-page-99.htm">F scale</a>” developed in 1947 by philosopher Theodor Adorno to measure the aspiration to fascism in Western societies. While the F scale is no longer widely used today, scientific literature on SDO expands each year (about <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://scholar.google.fr/scholar?q=%22social+dominance+orientation%22&amp;hl=fr&amp;as_sdt=0&amp;as_vis=1&amp;oi=scholart&amp;sa=X&amp;ved=0ahUKEwilvI_IrKLNAhUCPhQKHdrGAwAQgQMIHDAA">6000 articles</a> refer to it).</p>
</section>
<section id="a-clinical-picture-mixing-racism-sexism-lack-of-empathy-and-environmental-indifference" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-clinical-picture-mixing-racism-sexism-lack-of-empathy-and-environmental-indifference"><strong>A Clinical Picture Mixing Racism, Sexism, Lack of Empathy, and Environmental Indifference</strong></h2>
<p>Firstly, individuals scoring high on the SDO scale are on average more racist and sexist than others (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://dash.harvard.edu/bitstream/handle/1/3207711/Sidanius_SocialDominanceOrientation.pdf?sequence=">PDF</a>). The link between SDO and racism persists among individuals from minority ethnicities, just as the link between SDO and sexism persists among women. Thus, even though white men generally score higher (the so-called invariance hypothesis; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/41512921/Social_Dominance_Orientation_and_the_Pol20160124-27414-zmunsg.pdf?AWSAccessKeyId=AKIAJ56TQJRTWSMTNPEA&amp;Expires=1470907083&amp;Signature=8wOHffs8CCzmVm9BXZrfnxRiqz0%3D&amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B%20filename%3DSocial_dominance_orientation_and_the_pol.pdf">PDF</a>), the psychological mechanisms of dominance are active in all members of our society.</p>
<p>Additionally, Sandra Duarte, Michel Dambrun, and Serge Guimond—French researchers specializing in SDO—have shown that the relationship between legitimizing social hierarchies and sexist or racist prejudices persists even when analyses are adjusted for left-right political positioning (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Michael_Dambrun/publication/278327481_La_dominance_sociale_et_les_mythes_legitimateurs_validation_d%27une_version_francaise_de_l%27echelle_d%27orientation_a_la_dominance_sociale/links/5583ce5408ae8bf4ba6fa976.pdf?origin=publication_detail">PDF</a>). In other words, the tool captures a phenomenon that transcends our traditional political categories.</p>
<p>More interestingly, individuals with high SDO also tend to experience less empathy, defined as “the ability to put oneself in another’s shoes and perceive what they feel.” This is particularly true when the other belongs to a different social group (an exogroup; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/31217565/JOP_2013_Empathy_and_SDO.pdf?AWSAccessKeyId=AKIAJ56TQJRTWSMTNPEA&amp;Expires=1470908419&amp;Signature=aRCxMJ6WZoNPwS0hJSREMFuqkxs%3D&amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B%20filename%3DYoure_Inferior_and_Not_Worth_Our_Concern.pdf">PDF</a>). Since the absence of empathy and SDO mutually reinforce over time (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/31217565/JOP_2013_Empathy_and_SDO.pdf?AWSAccessKeyId=AKIAJ56TQJRTWSMTNPEA&amp;Expires=1470908419&amp;Signature=aRCxMJ6WZoNPwS0hJSREMFuqkxs%3D&amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B%20filename%3DYoure_Inferior_and_Not_Worth_Our_Concern.pdf">PDF</a>), one cannot help but think of the consequences of Manuel Valls’s recent remarks that ” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://www.liberation.fr/debats/2016/01/12/culture-de-l-excuse-les-sociologues-repondent-a-valls_1425855">explaining jihadism is already excusing it</a>.”</p>
<p>Finally, it has recently been demonstrated that those who legitimize dominance relations between individuals and groups are also more likely to legitimize human dominance over other living species. This is evidenced by a large <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://psp.sagepub.com/content/early/2013/06/19/0146167213490805">study</a> from 2013 showing that SDO clearly correlates with numerous “environmental attitudes”: individuals or populations scoring high on this scale are less likely to believe in human-caused climate change and promote a more utilitarian relationship with nature. If Donald Trump knows <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://www.lemonde.fr/elections-americaines/article/2016/05/27/etats-unis-donald-trump-promet-d-annuler-l-accord-de-paris-sur-le-climat-une-fois-elu_4927353_829254.html">something</a> about this, the socialists governing us are no less responsible, as evidenced by the death of Rémi Fraisse at the Sievens dam or their obstinacy in the Notre-Dame-des-Landes case.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-legitimizing-myths" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="the-legitimizing-myths"><strong>The “Legitimizing Myths”</strong></h2>
<p>The effects mentioned here are not exhaustive, but they help us understand why sexism, racism, lack of empathy, and environmental indifference often go hand in hand: there is an underlying belief in all these attitudes that social inequalities and dominance relations are <em>natural</em> or even <em>desirable</em>. These are known as legitimizing myths.</p>
<p>Today, the most powerful of these myths is probably that of meritocracy, which stipulates that the dominant “deserve” their position of power and the advantages that come with it, notwithstanding the <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://www.inegalites.fr/spip.php?article648">disintegration of social mobility</a>. But there are others, more insidious, such as adherence to social Darwinism (the idea that society will improve if the strongest have power), the naturalization of social hierarchies (the idea that some are genetically programmed to dominate and others to obey), or cultural representations like “religiosity is a more primitive attitude than atheism,” “egalitarianism is a utopia,” “true democracy is impossible in the current world,” “people are stupid,” etc., etc.</p>
<p>At the societal level and in the long term, the frequency and intensity of high SDO signs among our leaders should alert us to the very low ideological and intellectual diversity of the political class. This uniformity results primarily from the endogamy within the ruling classes (see <em>Ghettos du Gotha</em>, by Monique Pinçon-Charlot and Michel Pinçon; <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://inventin.lautre.net/livres/Les-ghettos-du-Gotha-Pincon.pdf">PDF</a>). Unfortunately, in the absence of a revolution renewing the entire political class, only republican education and evolving mentalities can combat this vicious circle.</p>
</section>
<section id="what-to-do" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="what-to-do"><strong>What to Do?</strong></h2>
<p>To move forward, we must first stop turning away from politics because current politicians no longer represent us. As philosopher Herbert Marcuse writes, “the ability to freely elect masters does not abolish either masters or slaves,” but abstaining from voting and dismissing this issue that concerns us all leaves the way open for the most mediocre masters and embraces <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://fr.wiktionary.org/wiki/kakistocratie">kakistocracy</a>.</p>
<p>Raising awareness of the importance of environmental and developmental factors that reinforce existing social hierarchies and/or facilitate social submission is also crucial. A study in France demonstrated the link between SDO and belief in genetic determinism of behavior, while understanding basic sociological principles can reduce scores (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Michael_Dambrun/publication/229641177_Why_Does_Social_Dominance_Orientation_Decrease_with_University_Exposure_to_the_Social_Sciences_The_Impact_of_Institutional_Socialization_and_the_Mediating_Role_of_Geneticism/links/5581ae0108aeab1e4666daa5.pdf">PDF</a>). To fill these gaps, reading books by Jared Diamond such as <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://www.gallimard.fr/Catalogue/GALLIMARD/NRF-Essais/De-l-inegalite-parmi-les-societes"><em>Guns, Germs, and Steel</em></a> (Pulitzer Prize 1998) or the shorter and magnificent essay by Henri Laborit <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/http://inventin.lautre.net/livres/Henri-Laborit-Eloge-de-la-fuite.pdf"><em>Praise of Flight</em></a>, which was also adapted into a film in Alain Resnais’s My American Uncle (<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=FQcC-VB_W-s">watch</a> for free on YouTube), is highly recommended.</p>
<p>The psychological mechanisms that allow brash individuals like Manuel Valls to seduce France are actually at work in each of us. Among them, Leon Festinger’s famous ” <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20170503132158/https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dissonance_cognitive#Paradigme_de_la_justification_de_l.27effort">cognitive dissonance</a>“—whereby our beliefs adjust <em>a posteriori</em> to the actions we take—features prominently. To grasp the essence of this idea, a concrete example can be useful.</p>
<p>A deserving and well-intentioned graduate of a prestigious school enters a large company. After cutting his teeth on a few unimportant projects, he quickly climbs the ladder and soon finds himself forced to make decisions <em>contrary</em> to his initial value system, whether to keep his job or advance his career. Laying off productive elements, speculating on raw materials, avoiding corporate taxes, etc.: so many decisions that—while delighting his shareholders—undoubtedly exacerbate the social inequalities he might have denounced in high school.</p>
<p>This tension—or dissonance—between our values and behaviors results in a certain mental and emotional discomfort that calls for either modifying the behaviors in question (e.g., resigning) or modifying the values causing the guilt and discomfort. We frequently observe a shift in attitude toward social hierarchy, somewhere between ages 25 and 40, such that once-condemned dominance relationships are gradually considered legitimate and natural. There is a reversal in the relationship between belief and action that few individuals are willing to acknowledge, although the phenomenon is universally recognized by psychologists and applies equally to those who rise in political, academic, or financial spheres.</p>
<p>Of course, this transition is not without doubts, but being usually accompanied by a refocusing of the social reference group, it generally comes to fruition. The lure of gain and desire for material comfort also play a crucial role, compensating for submission to the system as a whole.</p>
<p>Fighting for a fairer society thus requires the courage to argue with those who contribute to injustice without necessarily realizing it. And then it requires the intelligence to reconcile. If we want to prevent the inner conflicts caused by hierarchical success from systematically resolving by increased legitimization of existing dominance relations, it is essential to maintain communication with those whose fingers are caught in the gears.</p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>politics</category>
  <category>inequalities</category>
  <category>psychiatry</category>
  <category>cognitive sciences</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/thosewhodontgiveaf/</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/thosewhodontgiveaf/dore_quisenfoutent.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Neuroimaging of LSD: A World First at the Frontiers of Science</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Neuro89</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>This Monday, a new chapter <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2016/04/05/1518377113.full">opened</a> in the tumultuous history of lysergic acid diethylamide (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lysergic_acid_diethylamide">LSD</a>), whose psychedelic effects – “soul-revealing,” in Greek – were discovered in 1943 by chemist <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Albert_Hofmann">Albert Hofmann</a> (1906-2008).</p>
<p>Although psychedelic substances like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mescaline">mescaline</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Datura">datura</a>, or <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psilocybin">psilocybin</a> have been used for millennia in various parts of the world (India, South America), their neurobiological mode of action remains mysterious, and LSD is no exception.</p>
<p>While it is known that they involve the serotonergic system (like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MDMA">MDMA</a> or antidepressants), the link between these chemical changes and the observed cognitive effects remains almost unknown.</p>
<p>How can such small doses (a few dozen micrograms) cause such profound changes in consciousness, alter the perception of colors, sounds, and others, or generate those strange “revelations” that sometimes resemble personal, professional, or even spiritual points of no return?</p>
<section id="animals-on-lsd" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="animals-on-lsd">Animals on LSD</h2>
<p>This is the question a group of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neuroimaging">neuroimagers</a> and British psychiatrists attempted to answer, aided by a <a href="http://walacea.com/campaigns/lsd/">crowdfunding campaign</a> launched in 2015.</p>
<p>Since the scandal caused in the 1960s at Harvard by the research of <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Timothy_Leary">Timothy Leary</a> (proponent of “therapeutic LSD” <a href="http://www.laviedesidees.fr/LSD-le-retour-de-l-enfant-terrible.html">imprisoned</a> under Nixon’s presidency), the substance had been almost exclusively administered to animals (and occasionally to a few communists tortured in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Project_MKUltra">CIA secret laboratories</a>).</p>
<p>In animals, LSD is typically considered from a pathological rather than a therapeutic angle – namely, as a model of “induced psychosis” useful for mimicking certain aspects of schizophrenia.</p>
</section>
<section id="crowdfunding-to-the-rescue" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="crowdfunding-to-the-rescue">Crowdfunding to the Rescue</h2>
<p>LSD and psychedelics have thus been out of the scientific and clinical psychology perimeter for nearly 50 years, despite the continued interest of intellectuals like <a href="https://bibliobs.nouvelobs.com/essais/20091125.BIB4479/quand-sartre-voyait-des-homards-partout.html">Sartre</a>, <a href="http://www.vacarme.org/article2024.html">Foucault</a>, Huxley [<a href="http://www.eboga.fr/VIP/Aldous-Huxley-Les-portes-de-la-perception.pdf">PDF</a>], or Castaneda [<a href="http://data0.eklablog.com/ae-editions/perso/bibliotheque%20-%20pdf/carlos%20castaneda%20-%20l-herbe%20du%20diable%20et%20la%20pet.pdf">PDF</a>].</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/cosmos.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="432"></p>
<figcaption>Cosmos - Armelle Boussidan</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>However, with the advent of cognitive neuroscience and <a href="http://www.vidal.fr/actualites/15581/une_meta_analyse_confirme_l_interet_de_la_ketamine_dans_le_traitement_d_urgence_de_la_depression/">the discovery</a> of ketamine’s antidepressant potential in the early 2000s, it seemed inevitable that a few “daredevils” would eventually succumb to curiosity and decide to scrutinize LSD using new neuroimaging tools like MRI and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Magnetoencephalography">magnetoencephalography</a>.</p>
<p>This has been achieved thanks to the <a href="http://walacea.com/campaigns/lsd/">crowdfunding</a> employed by researchers David Nutt, Amanda Feilding, and Robin Carhart-Harris to bypass the reluctance of traditional funding agencies and conduct the first neuroimaging experiment entirely dedicated to LSD.</p>
</section>
<section id="about-twenty-testers" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="about-twenty-testers">About Twenty Testers</h2>
<p>Renowned psychiatrist David Nutt is known for his radical stance against excessive alcohol consumption in the UK and for his unusual discourse on certain drugs like <a href="http://rue89.nouvelobs.com/2012/06/29/de-lecstasy-pour-guerir-la-tete-le-combat-dun-chercheur-anglais-233430">MDMA and THC</a>.</p>
<p>Although his approach has sparked intense debates within the <a href="http://www.dailymail.co.uk/wires/pa/article-2980208/Brits-controversial-LSD-study.html">scientific community</a> and among some <a href="https://news.vice.com/article/lsd-research-mental-illnesses">users</a>, his method has just borne its first fruits: a publication in the journal of the American Academy of Sciences (<a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/early/2016/04/05/1518377113.full">PNAS</a>).</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/lsdstudy.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="430"></p>
<figcaption>One of the volunteers, before entering the scanner - walacea.com</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>About twenty individuals participated in a carefully crafted protocol combining MRI (for the spatial localization of brain activities) and magnetoencephalography (for their temporal characterization).</p>
<p>To isolate the activities specifically modified by LSD, each participant had to undergo the entire protocol twice:</p>
<ul>
<li>After ingesting the substance;</li>
<li>After ingesting a biologically inactive placebo.</li>
</ul>
<p>During each session, rest periods alternated with listening to music or watching silent films. For this first publication, only the rest periods were analyzed, but they are already rich in information.</p>
</section>
<section id="seeing-with-eyes-closed" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="seeing-with-eyes-closed">“Seeing” with Eyes Closed</h2>
<ul>
<li><p>At very small doses (less than 50 micrograms), LSD simply produces a feeling of euphoria, stimulates creativity, or heightens perception, making reality appear more beautiful and meaningful, but it does not necessarily induce hallucinations in the strict sense of the term.</p></li>
<li><p>In contrast, at the intermediate dose used in the study (75 micrograms), sensitive users already experience complex, dynamic, and colorful visual imagery, mainly perceptible in darkness. With a few distortions, the external world appears normal when the eyes are open, while rich hallucinations manifest as soon as the eyelids close.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>To explain this phenomenon, the researchers analyzed the “functional connectivity” of different brain areas [<a href="http://www.sfnrcongres.net/archivesite/www/2013/pdf/presentations2013/10h45%20Nicolas%20Menjot.pdf">PDF</a>].</p>
<p>They found that the coupling of activities between the primary visual area V1 (in pink) and the rest of the brain (red-yellow areas) was significantly enhanced by LSD – and this enhancement correlated with the intensity of the hallucinations reported by the subjects.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/reseaux.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="451"></p>
<figcaption>Top: increased connectivity between V1 (in pink) and the rest of the brain (from red to yellow). Bottom: correlation between this increase and the intensity of visual hallucinations experienced - Carhart-Harris et al., 2016, PNAS</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>These results suggest that the substance may allow us to “see” what is happening in our own brain by disinhibiting certain “reentrant” connections via type 5HT2A serotonergic receptors.</p>
<p>According to <a href="http://mentalfloss.com/article/78408/neuroimaging-reveals-how-lsd-affects-brain">Robin Carhart-Harris</a>, leader of the study:</p>
<p><em>“With LSD, neural networks partially lose their integrity. Brain systems become less segregated, and different networks start to merge with each other. Overall, the brain becomes more connected and operates more flexibly.”</em></p>
</section>
<section id="new-horizons" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="new-horizons">New Horizons</h2>
<p>The analysis of electrophysiological signals (MEG) also shows that LSD induces a general decrease in the power of electromagnetic oscillations on the scalp surface, coupled with an acceleration of the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alpha_wave">alpha</a> rhythm.</p>
<p>This rhythm is directly linked to attentional processes, and a popular hypothesis suggests it is involved in the <a href="http://www.tandfonline.com/doi/abs/10.4161/cib.22702">filtering</a> of information processed by our brain. If replicable and robust, these unexpected results will be thoroughly examined, cited, and commented on in the near future.</p>
<p>Underlying these findings, David Nutt and Robin Carhart-Harris’s work provides a more scientific foundation for an old hypothesis proposed by Aldous Huxley in “The Doors of Perception” [1954, <a href="http://www.eboga.fr/VIP/Aldous-Huxley-Les-portes-de-la-perception.pdf">PDF</a>], an influential book that Jim Morrison used to name his band (“The Doors”).</p>
<p>According to Huxley (also author of “Brave New World”), psychedelics suppress a persistent tendency of our brain to prioritize the processing of what is useful for survival and reproduction, at the expense of the countless other sources of information that surround and constitute it.</p>
<p>By weakening the multiple filters that normally force our thinking to stay “usefully glued” to reality, LSD thus opens refreshing horizons to consciousness. Among these are the filters that usually prevent us from “seeing” the dynamic content generated by our own brain!</p>
</section>
<section id="dissolving-the-ego-in-a-scanner" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="dissolving-the-ego-in-a-scanner">“Dissolving the Ego” in a Scanner?</h2>
<p>Already astounding on a perceptual level, the action of LSD does not stop at “closed-eye” hallucinations, nor even at those – more or less disturbing – that persist with higher doses when the eyes are open.</p>
<p>If this were the case, painting and cinema could almost transcribe the experience and allow the novice to grasp its essence. But with higher doses and in certain contexts, LSD and other indolic hallucinogens facilitate the emergence of a state impossible to describe verbally or pictorially.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/innergardens.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="530"></p>
<figcaption>“Timeless inner garden” - Armelle Boussidan</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Some call this drastic alteration of affective, spatial, and temporal relationships with reality “ego dissolution.”</p>
<p>For <a href="http://mentalfloss.com/article/78408/neuroimaging-reveals-how-lsd-affects-brain">Dr.&nbsp;Carhart-Harris</a>:</p>
<p><em>“The phenomenon is often accompanied by new insights about ourselves, our journey, our relationships with others, and the world in general. In fact, it goes hand in hand with spiritual and mystical feelings.”</em></p>
<p>These extremely intimate experiences often <a href="http://leportique.revues.org/155">lead</a> to a more serene apprehension of death, making LSD useful for <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC4086777/">relieving</a> some terminally ill patients, and they justify the use of the term “<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Entheogen">entheogen</a>” (which “brings one closer to the divine”) to describe the action of psychedelics – whereas more superficial drugs like MDMA are simply called empathogens (which “bring one closer to others”).</p>
</section>
<section id="highly-subjective-experiences" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="highly-subjective-experiences">Highly Subjective Experiences</h2>
<p>Although the spiritual dimension of LSD is a priori foreign (and somewhat contrary) to the premises of scientific reasoning, the study authors still wanted to know if “ego dissolution” had a neurobiological counterpart in their data.</p>
<p>To do this, they cross-referenced the quantitative questionnaires filled out by the subjects (see below) with the various brain signals collected.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/asq.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>Subjective effects of LSD intake - Carhart-Harris et al., 2016, PNAS</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>MRI signal analyses confirm what has already been observed in consumers of <a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0118143">ayahuasca</a> and <a href="https://www.pnas.org/content/109/6/2138.full">psilocybin</a>, namely that there appears to be a correlation between feelings of “ego dissolution” and the modification of functional coupling in three structures belonging to a “default mode network” connected repeatedly to self-referential thinking and the concept of “self.”</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/oscillations.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="462"></p>
<figcaption>Decrease (in blue) in electromagnetic oscillatory power in different frequency bands induced by LSD, potentially linked to the phenomenon of “ego dissolution” according to the study authors - Carhart-Harris et al., 2016, PNAS</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Furthermore, electrophysiological data suggest that this dissolution is accompanied by large-scale desynchronization of alpha rhythms, possibly corresponding to the suppression of certain inhibitory mechanisms active in so-called “normal” states of consciousness.</p>
<p>Without prejudging the quality of the analyses conducted, there is, however, reason to be slightly skeptical about the possibility of inducing (and quantifying) genuine “ego dissolution” in a scanner with such moderate doses of LSD.</p>
<p>The interpretation of the results is subject to caution, especially since unlike visual hallucinations (potentially quantifiable by rigorous tests), spiritual feelings are highly subjective and personal, making them difficult to objectify through a questionnaire.</p>
</section>
<section id="at-the-border-between-science-and-spirituality" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="at-the-border-between-science-and-spirituality">At the Border between Science and Spirituality</h2>
<p>In conclusion, research on LSD undeniably holds great potential for fundamental neuroscience and psychiatry, but the excessive rationalization of the psychedelic experience also carries a double risk.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>On the one hand, the association between psychedelic states and brain activities might suggest that the former are explained by the latter, which is both false and illusory. It is crucial to remember that researchers interpret correlations (between mental and brain states) that never constitute proof of causality and do not exhaust the richness of the associated experiences.</p></li>
<li><p>On the other hand, when neuroimaging looks at <a href="http://www.lesechos.fr/04/09/2015/la-meditation-validee-par-les-neurosciences.htm">meditation</a>, <a href="http://www.lemonde.fr/sciences/article/2013/11/11/dieu-adn-et-depression_3511843_1650684.html">religious fervor</a>, or psychedelics, it sometimes gives the impression of mixing genres and blurring boundaries that generally allow scientific rationality and spirituality to protect each other. The foremost of these boundaries is perhaps the distinction between the quest for objective truth and the quest for meaning, which occurs in the realm of subjectivity.</p></li>
</ul>
<section id="a-hint-of-prevention" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-hint-of-prevention">A Hint of Prevention</h3>
<p>Although the biological toxicity of LSD is considered almost nil (unlike most synthetic drugs, including MDMA), its potential psychological toxicity should not be overlooked. While LSD does not deteriorate physical or mental health at the population level (there is even a tendency towards the <a href="http://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0063972">opposite</a>), its consumption can cause problems at the individual level.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>Firstly, it can sometimes reveal latent schizophrenia or other psychiatric disorders in young subjects [<a href="https://wiki.dmt-nexus.me/w/images/7/72/Long_term_effects_of_lsd.pdf">PDF</a>].</p></li>
<li><p>Secondly, LSD is more frequently associated than other psychedelics with the occurrence of disorders known as <a href="http://www.cairn.info/revue-psychotropes-2005-1-page-9.htm">hallucinogen-persisting perception disorders</a>, including a temporary resurgence of symptoms normally related to acute consumption (the famous “flashback” or acid flashback), visual disturbances (such as the <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/6980680?dopt=Abstract">reduced</a> ability to discriminate colors), and various emotional instabilities.</p></li>
<li><p>Thirdly, by temporarily expanding consciousness, the psychedelic experience sometimes leads the individual to consider new questions and new representations of the self, the world, and others. Currently considered <a href="http://journals.cambridge.org/action/displayAbstract?fromPage=online&amp;aid=10261226&amp;fileId=S0033291715002901">beneficial in the long term</a>, these events can be disorienting in the short term for the user and their surroundings, especially if the hallucinogens are poorly understood (hence the usefulness of disseminating scientific knowledge on the subject).</p></li>
</ul>
<p>Besides the fact that taking LSD remains perfectly illegal, it can occasionally be harmful, especially for those under 25, severely hypertensive individuals, and more generally when it occurs in emotionally negative contexts.</p>
<p>Simultaneous ingestion of large quantities of stimulants or alcohol is strongly discouraged (as it facilitates the occurrence of paranoid episodes and the disinhibition of certain risky behaviors).</p>
<p><strong>Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/BaharGholipour">Bahar Gholipour</a> for providing the publication before its official release.</strong></p>
<p><a href="https://www.nouvelobs.com/rue89/rue89-neuro89/20160412.RUE2304/la-neuroimagerie-du-lsd-une-premiere-mondiale-aux-frontieres-de-la-science.html"><strong>Link to the original article</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> </script>


</section>
</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>neuro89</category>
  <category>psychedelics</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>psychiatry</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 11 Apr 2016 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/lsdneuroimaging/innergardens.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Between 1 Euro and 1 Billion: Your Budget for Eternal Life</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Neuro89</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Are you fed up with the human condition and tired of ear hair? Do you wonder why your deserving ego should dissolve into the great Nothing that is the great All?</p>
<p>This manual is for you. It outlines the main steps to keep alive the wild hope of eternal life. Against all odds, nature, and everything else!</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/evitement1.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>“Evitement #1” - Antoine Doré</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>However, eternal life has become a business that requires you to ask yourself a crucial question: how much to invest?</p>
<ul>
<li>With 1 euro…</li>
<li>Between 1 and 100 euros</li>
<li>Between 100 and 1,000 euros</li>
<li>Between 1,000 and 10,000 euros</li>
<li>Between 10,000 and 100,000 euros</li>
<li>Between 100,000 and 1,000,000 euros</li>
<li>Between 1,000,000 and 1,000,000,000 euros</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Any resemblance between this pyramid-shaped table of contents and any social hierarchy is purely coincidental.</em></p>
<section id="with-1-euro" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="with-1-euro">With 1 euro…</h2>
<p>With this symbolic euro, light a candle in front of the local patron saint and pray, because as Blaise Pascal says in his famous wager:</p>
<p><em>“Let us weigh the gain and the loss in wagering that God is. Let us estimate these two chances: if you win, you win everything; if you lose, you lose nothing. Wager, then, without hesitation that He is.”</em> (Pensées, 1670)</p>
<p>Incidentally, stop smoking, this should help you finance the next steps. If you do not wish to quit smoking, question your motivations: are you really a serious candidate for immortality?</p>
<p>Otherwise, stay calm and try to help others around you to be calm as well. In the absence of resources, they are your best survival asset: without a social group or in a troubled social group, you risk depression or anxiety [<a href="http://ppw.kuleuven.be/okp/_pdf/FriedInPressFLTLT.pdf">PDF</a>], which tend to be poorly tolerated when they last too long…</p>
</section>
<section id="between-1-and-100-euros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="between-1-and-100-euros">Between 1 and 100 euros</h2>
<p>Let’s be honest: this amount is a bit tight for immortality. As hope supposedly keeps us alive, start by putting 2 euros and a Euromillions ticket in a drawer.</p>
<p>Then invest in a good pair of shoes and start jogging. In reasonable doses, sport has great virtues for an organ that needs special care because, unlike the liver, heart, or lungs, it is not easily replaceable: the brain.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/hippocampe.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="486"></p>
<figcaption>Immuno-stained hippocampal section - Harvard.edu/Brainbow</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Even though it is estimated that it would take about 3,000 years for a human brain to lose half of its neurons, it would be a pity to live as long as Highlander if you have Alzheimer’s. Fortunately, <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/25331877">physical exercise</a> is a key factor in neurogenesis in the hippocampus, the brain structure that stores your memories.</p>
</section>
<section id="between-100-and-1000-euros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="between-100-and-1000-euros">Between 100 and 1,000 euros</h2>
<p>Have you quit smoking and taken up sport? Among the other measures to take while waiting for the elixir of youth that will grant you eternal life, watch your diet. Not too much alcohol, soda, gluten, red meat, fish… How about a little dandelion juice with your broccoli?</p>
<p>Stop! That would be too simple. As our national Elise Lucet has shown, water, fruits, vegetables, or milk from traditional agriculture still contain too many of those damned pesticides. You will often need a little more money to eat more organically. Annoying, yes, but the link between these chemicals and diseases like Parkinson’s is so clear that it is officially considered a <a href="http://www.lemonde.fr/planete/article/2012/05/09/le-lien-entre-la-maladie-de-parkinson-et-les-pesticides-officiellement-reconnu_1698543_3244.html">professional disease</a> among farmers. It even seems that the accumulation of pesticides due to too much milk consumption (more than 0.5L/day) may <a href="http://www.neurology.org/content/early/2015/12/09/WNL.0000000000002254">facilitate</a> the emergence of associated symptoms.</p>
<p>Compared to other substances, the impact of pesticides is easily objectifiable because dopaminergic neurons – which pesticides target – are a rare and fragile resource. Largely grouped in a small nucleus in the middle of the brain, they represent roughly <a href="http://lecerveau.mcgill.ca/flash/d/d_03/d_03_m/d_03_m_que/d_03_m_que.html">less than 0.5% of all your neurons</a>, but they are involved in countless cognitive functions: learning, movement, decision-making, mood, motivation, attention, and concentration, to name a few.</p>
<p>Luckily, the nutritional problem is fairly simple for us French: partly linked to wine (red) consumption, rich in <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Resv%C3%A9ratrol">resveratrol</a>, the <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Paradoxe_fran%C3%A7ais">“French paradox”</a> allows our gastronomy to be quite advanced on longevity issues despite certain rule breaches. If you can afford it, the pleasure of eating well will easily surpass the desire to eat a lot.</p>
</section>
<section id="between-1000-and-10000-euros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="between-1000-and-10000-euros">Between 1,000 and 10,000 euros</h2>
<p>Congratulations, with this amount, you can afford health insurance! More than <a href="http://www.europe1.fr/sante/ces-francais-sans-mutuelle-2265917">3 million French</a> do not have this chance. It will replace your teeth, glasses, and other hearing aids in the centuries to come. Because even if gene therapy allowed your cells to regenerate indefinitely, even if you spent eternity in a sterile room eating pasteurized food, good old physical-chemical erosion would continue to wear out all the inert elements that make you up.</p>
<p>With the dismantling of public health services, your insurance may also have to pay for your potential cancer, whose occurrence will be more likely the longer you live. Indeed, cancer remains <a href="http://www.lemonde.fr/planete/article/2015/01/01/cancers-le-role-du-hasard-reevalue_4548347_3244.html">a highly random process</a> that can never be completely curbed by eliminating external risk factors. It’s frustrating, but this risk will indeed approach 100% if you manage to extend your longevity by several centuries (compared to 50% for a “normal” life of 70 or 80 years). Ironically, immortality is a cardinal property of many cancerous lineages, the most famous being the <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/HeLa">HeLa</a> strain.</p>
<p>Also, keep part of this budget for distractions and entertainment. Otherwise, your hypothetical immortality could become deadly boring. Start by buying a pair of Google Glass! In addition to supporting these apostles of <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Calico_(entreprise)">“death defeated”</a> in their philanthropic endeavor, acquiring this technological gem that you do not (yet) need could help you overcome the small dangers of daily life. In other words, those that mere mortals can afford to neglect but could seriously jeopardize your immortality plans: automatic detection of potential terrorists in the street, real-time driving aid, lightning strike probability, etc.</p>
<p>Always remember, if the mere mortal can compensate with a life rich in emotions and meaning, the “opportunity cost” associated with an avoidable death tends towards infinity for an aspirant to immortality, like the number of years that would have been so foolishly lost.</p>
</section>
<section id="between-10000-and-100000-euros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="between-10000-and-100000-euros">Between 10,000 and 100,000 euros</h2>
<p>At this stage, you will start enjoying some services that most of your fellow citizens cannot afford. Before proceeding, please check if you have paid your taxes for those who cannot afford health insurance, because you wouldn’t want to live eternally with an irritating pack of “toothless” people under your windows, would you?</p>
<p>Once this formality is done, first go to the <a href="http://www.american-hospital.org/fr/notre-offre-de-soins/bilans-de-sante-prevention.html">Check-up Center</a> of the American Hospital in Neuilly-sur-Seine. You will spend <a href="https://tempsreel.nouvelobs.com/l-enquete-de-l-obs/20120323.OBS4482/l-hopital-americain-le-palace-des-people-et-du-business.html">about 5,000 euros</a> for an exhaustive health check that should help curb many lesions and diseases at their earliest stage. Cardiac ultrasound, lung scan, extensive blood tests, body fat percentage: immortality is a daily battle that requires you to learn to love hospitals and doctors!</p>
<p>Back home, open your web browser and visit the website of <a href="http://www.illumina.com/">Illumina</a>, the world leader in genetic sequencing for individuals. For about 1,000 euros, you will get a complete transcription of your genome on DVD. But as it would be utterly pointless to examine these 3 billion A, T, C, G letters under Microsoft Word, you will need the services of a greedy team of bioinformaticians and professional geneticists to “decode” your genetic identity (for example, at <a href="http://cyphergenomics.com/">Cypher Genomics</a>). If needed, their results could help you benefit more easily from targeted therapies – that is, <a href="http://www.lesechos.fr/idees-debats/sciences-prospective/02190124115-cancer-le-pari-des-therapies-ciblees-1123952.php">adapted to your genetic identity</a> and its weaknesses.</p>
<p>In another vein, we also recommend investing in a heavy and possibly elevated car. In the long term, the automotive risk factor should not be overlooked, and no biotechnology has yet proven effective in road accidents (<a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mortalit%C3%A9_en_France#Causes_de_mortalit.C3.A9">fourth leading cause of death</a>). Well-filled wallets will be happy to learn that SUV and sedan drivers can reduce this risk <a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0001457502001355">by two or three times</a>, as the weight of their car is an advantage in many types of collisions.</p>
<p>Welcome also, the armored bodywork that will help protect you from itinerant crime and civil wars that socioeconomic inequalities might favor in the coming decades.</p>
</section>
<section id="between-100000-and-1000000-euros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="between-100000-and-1000000-euros">Between 100,000 and 1,000,000 euros</h2>
<p>Sorry, but the biomedical field has little more to offer you. Certainly, your substantial budget might eventually give you access to some emerging techniques like <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadronth%C3%A9rapie">hadron therapy</a> (extremely precise radiation therapy), replacement organs (available <a href="http://www.courrierinternational.com/article/2009/01/29/le-trafic-d-organes-se-porte-bien">on the black market</a>), as well as the most advanced bioprostheses – like this artificial heart designed by <a href="http://www.carmatsa.com/?lang=fr">Carmat</a>. Hurrah for France. But this is where the fantasy of immortality becomes thick with serious doubt.</p>
<p>With such a budget, be sure that cryogenic companies like <a href="http://www.alcor.org/">Alcor</a> or <a href="http://www.cryonics.org/">Cryonics</a> will welcome you with open arms for a freezing (-196°C) scheduled right after your true-false “death.” Admittedly, they are both very fringe science, but only Cryonics imposes neither a post-mortem maximum delay nor <a href="http://www.cryonics.org/emergency-situations/deceased-non-member">pre-cryopreservation treatment</a>. Needless to say, upon your awakening, Liliane Bettencourt might easily outpace you in both running and sudoku. So, if you are a bit tight for full cryopreservation at Alcor (200,000 dollars), you will have a dilemma between Alcor’s “head option” (this is called <a href="http://www.alcor.org/AtWork/index.html">neurocryopreservation</a>: 80,000 dollars) and “whole body option” at Cryonics. It’s up to you whether immortality without sexual organs appeals to you.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/evitement2.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="413"></p>
<figcaption>“Evitement #2” - Antoine Doré</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Many people have heard of cryogenics without knowing what to expect exactly. And for a good reason: nobody really knows. These companies also warn that the hope placed in cryogenic techniques depends entirely on future research, whose contours we still struggle to imagine. Two equally improbable “solutions” loom on the horizon…</p>
<p>Firstly, you can hope for the emergence of those highly sophisticated nanorobots necessary to repair the damage freezing has done to your tissues. But to be honest, the result might not be great. As mammal bodies have been evolving for 220 million years within a temperature range of at most <a href="http://www.evolution-biologique.org/histoire-de-la-vie/synapsides/l-homeothermie.html">25 to 45°C</a>, the chances are slim that a whole body will ever emerge intact from freezing (this is just an opinion), even if done optimally and maintained below -150°C.</p>
<p>The second solution is probably more realistic but assumes that consciousness and mind are purely mechanical phenomena. Indeed, some researchers in the field of <a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/sebastian_seung?language=fr">“connectomics”</a> have recently suggested that our mind could be reduced to how our billions of neurons are interconnected. Under this hypothesis, the rapid advances in magnetic resonance imaging raise the hope of possibly extracting (from, for example, a frozen head) the information contained in these neuronal “wiring diagrams” that constitute our mental identity. Cryogenics supporters thus argue that a computer could “host” a functional connectome, similar to how servers host websites today.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/connectome.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="283"></p>
<figcaption>Representation of the human connectome - RoyalSocietyPublishing.org/Olaf Sporns</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>However, your burgeoning enthusiasm should be doubly tempered here. Firstly, these diagrams will necessarily be extracted with some degree of uncertainty. Upon waking, you might no longer be sure: is your mother named Marianne or Marine? Secondly, as neurons are not inert transistors but functional units that perpetually modify according to very complex and individual laws, this supercomputer would need to host not only your connectome but also reproduce these countless parameters with great fidelity. Otherwise, you risk being yourself upon waking and “something” else a week later.</p>
</section>
<section id="between-1000000-and-1000000000-euros" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="between-1000000-and-1000000000-euros">Between 1,000,000 and 1,000,000,000 euros</h2>
<p>As a good millionaire, you no longer know what to do with your capital and you want to invest it in a long-term remunerative sector? In that case, know that immortality is an area where the notion of long-term takes on its full meaning!</p>
<p>Admittedly, your investments are unlikely to offer you personal immortality, but if you instill the cult of capital and social reproduction in your children and grandchildren, they might benefit from your foresight. But where to invest? Between us, the business model of cryogenics is not very promising. Opt instead for anti-aging research.</p>
<p>Among the companies most interested in your money, you will obviously find the irrepressible Google and its <a href="http://www.calicolabs.com/">Calico</a> laboratory. With the recruitment of the <a href="http://www.lemonde.fr/festival/article/2015/09/23/ray-kurzweil-le-salarie-de-google-qui-veut-terrasser-la-mort_4767845_4415198.html">controversial Ray Kurzweil</a> prophesying the imminent advent of a “technological singularity” (a sudden break in human history due to technology), Google has indeed become an openly “transhumanist” company. Aiming both at eradicating aging and developing robotics or the rise of artificial intelligences superior to the human mind, this multinational will undoubtedly achieve some feats in anti-aging in the coming decades.</p>
<p>But if you prefer more family-oriented companies, you can also opt for a donation to <a href="http://www.sens.org/">Sens.org</a> founded by Aubrey de Grey. This Sébastien Tellier of immortality has crystallized many hopes since the release of his docu-advertisement <a href="http://theimmortalists.com/">“The Immortalists”</a>. With the funds he tries to collect here and there, Aubrey de Grey is pursuing several relatively serious scientific avenues. Among them, de Grey seeks to control or reverse the degeneration of “telomeres,” these DNA sequences at the ends of chromosomes that act as natural protection against the degradation of your genetic heritage.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/immortalists.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="452"></p>
<figcaption>“The Immortalists”: “Live forever or die trying”</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Indeed, it is suspected that aging is largely due to the gradual disappearance of these sequences over a lifetime, and some studies in mice indicate that by artificially reconstructing or preventing the disappearance of telomeres, it might be possible to significantly slow aging, or even reverse it! For now, this type of intervention also tends to create tumors and other metabolic instabilities, but a longevity of 200 years will likely require such treatment.</p>
<p>If you are ready to take all risks to curb your own aging, then I recommend putting a substantial amount into Aubrey de Grey or another similar private foundation. Their gratitude might open the doors to certain pharmacies and give you access to <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sirolimus">rapamycin</a>, which is the first molecule recognized as effective in extending mammalian lifespan by a few percent (at the cost of some side effects already observed in mice, <a href="http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pubmed/22587563">such as testicular degeneration or cataracts</a>).</p>
<p>Unfortunately (or not), the immortality business has not yet really taken off in France and access to these experimental substances will pose more problems here. You could therefore opt for a more indirect approach if you want to invest in blue-white-red immortality. Among the possible solutions, tax-deductible donations to the <a href="http://www.cnrs.fr/fr/dons/dons.htm">CNRS</a>, <a href="http://www.inserm.fr/participer-a-la-recherche/faire-un-don">Inserm</a>, <a href="http://don.frm.org/donner">FRM</a>, or philanthropic organizations like the <a href="http://dons.fondationdefrance.org/multi/~mon-don/">Fondation de France</a>. These institutions also promote serious scientific research on aging, although their results are not initially reserved for the few “happy fews” to which you belong.</p>
<blockquote class="blockquote">
<h2 id="socioeconomic-gradients-health-gradients" class="anchored">Socioeconomic Gradients, Health Gradients</h2>
<p>While our benevolent government is about to deal a few more blows to the labor code, socioeconomic inequalities continue to translate into minds, bodies, and mortality rates [<a href="http://www.who.int/social_determinants/publications/health_in_an_unequal_world_marmott_lancet.pdf">PDF</a>]. Not to mention all the white-collar workers who <a href="https://blogs.mediapart.fr/communistes-unitaires/blog/150216/la-chemise-les-goodyear-et-nddl">suffer</a>.</p>
<p>Epidemiologists and ethicists have lamented for many years the slow progress of France in prevention, and they regret that Insee limits the publication of the most useful demographic data to evaluate the phenomenon. While it is starting to subside in many European countries, the correlation between social hierarchy and health tends to worsen in France, so that the mortality rate of workers is 2.5 times higher than that of executives [p31-p32, this <a href="http://www.hcsp.fr/explore.cgi/hcspr20091112_inegalites.pdf">PDF</a>].</p>
<p>The High Council for Public Health regularly reminds us <a href="http://www.hcsp.fr">of this</a>, without much effect.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><strong>Thanks</strong> to <a href="http://www.antoinedore.com/">Antoine Doré</a> for these illustrations depicting death grappling with the lucky recipient of a neurocryopreservation.</p>
<p>(<a href="https://www.nouvelobs.com/rue89/rue89-neuro89/20160221.RUE2257/entre-1-euro-et-1-milliard-votre-budget-pour-la-vie-eternelle.html"><strong>Link to the original article</strong></a>)</p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async=""> 
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>neuro89</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>future</category>
  <category>inequalities</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2016 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/eternallife/evitement1.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>The ‘Brain Behind the Attacks’ Taken Literally</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Neuro89</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/terroristbrain/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Every year, new words and expressions are born or revived in a public debate constantly stirred by the evolution of techniques and societies. Language exerts considerable, often implicit, influence on the formation of opinions, leading to an ongoing need to clarify its meaning and measure its impact.</p>
<p>Following the killings in France in 2015, an expression has become an almost indispensable term to denote our public enemy number one: the ‘brain behind the attacks,’ this depersonalized and multifaceted threat that thrives at times in Salafist mosques, at other times in the suburbs of Saint-Denis, and at other times in Syria.</p>
<p>Adopted by most of the media and numerous politicians, the ‘brain behind the attacks’ is one of those ready-made expressions that primarily reflect the difficulty, if not the abandonment, of thinking about terrorism beyond clichés and misleading rhetoric.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/terroristbrain/dore_cerveau_attentats.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The brain behind the attacks - Antoine Doré</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<section id="a-brain-for-ten-terrorists" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-brain-for-ten-terrorists">A Brain for Ten Terrorists?</h2>
<p>Taken literally, searching relentlessly for <em>the</em> brain behind attacks committed by a dozen individuals is akin to denying the existence of a unique psychology in those who acted. It reduces these suicide bombers to puppets whose brains are washed by an occult intelligence, external to our society and foreign to our culture. Dangerous due to its implicit nature, this representation of the situation is problematic at a time when we seek to deradicalize and thus understand the tiny fraction of French youth inclined toward <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jihad#Jihad_majeur_et_Jihad_mineur">‘minor jihad’</a>.</p>
<p>Yet there are reasons for hope. Over the past decade, some researchers have rigorously studied the determinants of terrorist violence. Simultaneously, neurobiologists and psychologists have made significant progress in understanding violent and antisocial behaviors. It is urgent that this knowledge enter the public debate, be considered by institutions, and be subject to serious investigation. This is also the aim of <a href="http://sciences.blogs.liberation.fr/home/2015/11/le-pdg-du-cnrs-veut-une-recherche-post-attentats.html">the call published on November 18, 2015</a> by Alain Fuchs, president of CNRS.</p>
</section>
<section id="is-the-brain-behind-the-attacks-a-sick-brain" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="is-the-brain-behind-the-attacks-a-sick-brain">Is the ‘Brain Behind the Attacks’ a ‘Sick Brain’?</h2>
<p>Although it is morally justifiable and understandable, the lexicon of madness and alienation (‘madmen’, ‘monsters’, ‘sick’, etc.) used to describe terrorists is rarely justified clinically. Indeed, numerous retrospective studies on IRA (Ireland), ETA (Basque Country), or Al-Qaeda fighters show that terrorists—whether Islamist or not—are most often within the ‘normal distribution’ concerning psychiatric pathologies, social origin, or education [<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Andrew_Silke/publication/238721660_Radicalization_Holy_Warriors_Exploring_the_Psychological_Processes_of_Jihadi/links/0a85e53c6983bcbf4a000000.pdf">PDF</a>]. In other words, there is no psychiatric, psychological, or socio-economic profile that is typical of a suicide terrorist.</p>
<p>Established and accepted in a report submitted to the U.S. Congress as early as 1999 [<a href="http://www.loc.gov/rr/frd/pdf-files/Soc_Psych_of_Terrorism.pdf">PDF</a>, page 40], this observation has also been discussed in the prestigious journal Science [<a href="https://hal-ens.archives-ouvertes.fr/ijn_00509568/document">PDF</a>, <a href="http://www.artisresearch.com/articles/Atran_Individual_Factors.pdf">PDF</a>] under the impetus of <a href="http://www.institutnicod.org/membres/membres-statutaires/atran-scott/">Scott Atran</a>. A pioneer in terrorism research, this Franco-American anthropologist also reminds us that the ‘success’ associated with jihadist engagement on Twitter or Facebook constitutes a motivation as simple as it is powerful for martyr candidates, sensitive to the respect and admiration aroused in some by their morbid project (see Atran’s <a href="https://youtu.be/qlbirlSA-dc">intervention</a> to the UN Security Council, in English, and the <a href="http://www.un.org/press/fr/2015/cs11872.doc.htm">French report</a> associated with it).</p>
<section id="a-paradoxical-altruism" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-paradoxical-altruism">A Paradoxical Altruism</h3>
<p>Psychologically, suicide bombing is more akin to what researchers call ‘altruistic punishment’ than to the murderous insanity responsible for the numerous shootings observed in the United States. The latter is often linked to a <a href="https://www.contrepoints.org/2012/12/19/108575-tuerie-a-lecole-la-piste-pharmaceutique">pre-existing mental pathology</a>, which explains Barack Obama’s efforts to strengthen <a href="https://tempsreel.nouvelobs.com/societe/20160105.AFP1922/armes-a-feu-aux-etats-unis-obama-decide-de-court-circuiter-le-congres.html">gun control</a> for individuals suffering from psychiatric illnesses. In contrast, altruistic punishment involves incurring a cost to restore a social norm (of cooperation or otherwise) that one considers more significant than personal interest. The support of other group members and the role of social norms play an important role in such behaviors.</p>
<p>Thus, whether terrorists aspire to Sharia or democratic sovereignty in Islamic lands makes little difference, as the support (real or presumed) of the social group to which they identify seems to be the primary cause of their actions. This is also why bidirectional exchange between Arab-Muslim and Judeo-Christian cultures is the first remedy against terrorism. Symbolized by the opening of synagogues, churches, and mosques or by the tolerance of religious symbols such as the kippah, the cross, and the veil, the construction of a sense of belonging to French society heavily depends on citizens’ ability to understand the emotions and moral feelings driving others beyond their usual social circle.</p>
<p>Although religious affiliation plays a crucial role since it overrides national belonging in the jihadists’ imagination, research shows that they are not born or raised in more religious environments than average [<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Andrew_Silke/publication/238721660_Radicalization_Holy_Warriors_Exploring_the_Psychological_Processes_of_Jihadi/links/0a85e53c6983bcbf4a000000.pdf">PDF</a>]. A <a href="http://www.pnas.org/content/113/2/316.abstract">study</a> conducted in Palestine even suggests that despite its ability to segment humanity into communities of beliefs, religious sentiment itself does not predispose one to view terrorism as a morally just cause.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/terroristbrain/dilemmetram.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The trolley problem, widely used to study moral decision-making</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Adapting the famous <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dilemme_du_tramway">‘trolley problem’</a>, researchers asked over 1000 young people whether it would be just to kill a Palestinian to save five Israelis or five Palestinians. The first group was asked to decide directly on the best course of action. The second group was asked which decision God would approve of the most. Contrary to the belief that religious beliefs are the epicenter of inter-ethnic violence, the second group was clearly more inclined than the first to sacrifice the Palestinian man to save Israeli lives…</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="can-violent-deviations-be-prevented-using-neuroscience" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="can-violent-deviations-be-prevented-using-neuroscience">Can Violent Deviations Be Prevented Using Neuroscience?</h2>
<p>If the terrorist is distinguished neither by their mental state, religiosity, education level, nor beliefs, how can we initiate neurobiological reflection? Let’s perhaps start with what makes a jihadist a criminal: premeditated violence and the act itself.</p>
<p>Scientifically, premeditated violence corresponds to proactive aggression, as opposed to reactive aggression. The causes and consequences of these two phenomena are very different. In 2015, a study conducted with over 250 adolescents showed that proactive violence might reflect a desire to attain high social status, while reactive violence would denote a low social status [<a href="https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Yvonne_Van_den_Berg3/publication/281318689_Popularity_Differentially_Predicts_Reactive_and_Proactive_Aggression_in_Early_Adolescence/links/55e1712808aecb1a7cc6631f.pdf">PDF</a>]. Moreover, while proactive violence is not or is only slightly dependent on circulating cortisol levels (the stress hormone), reactive violence is <a href="http://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s10802-008-9263-3">strongly</a> dependent on them. Finally, proactive aggression results more from a difficulty in experiencing emotions, while reactive aggression stems from an inability to regulate these emotions.</p>
<p>At the cerebral level, these findings <a href="http://archpsyc.jamanetwork.com/article.aspx?articleid=1847577'amp;resultclick=1">translate</a> in proactive violent individuals as hypo-reactivity of a central structure for emotions, the amygdala. In reactive violent individuals, on the other hand, there is an <a href="http://www.biologicalpsychiatryjournal.com/article/S0006-3223%2806%2901064-X/abstract?cc=y=">observed</a> hyper-reactivity of the same structure. Pursuing a promising research avenue, a research group even showed that <a href="http://scan.oxfordjournals.org/content/early/2015/02/12/scan.nsv018.abstract">mild electrical stimulation</a> of the anterior prefrontal cortex reduced levels of proactive aggression but had no effect on levels of reactive aggression.</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/terroristbrain/amygdale.png" class="img-fluid figure-img"></p>
<figcaption>The amygdala, a key structure for emotions - Anatomography/Wikimedia Commons/CC</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Given that stimulation of the anterior prefrontal cortex also modifies how individuals perceive dominance relationships with others, these results may reinforce the link between proactive violence and the quest for social status (see also the thesis defended by the author of this blog, <a href="https://drive.google.com/open?id=0Bw7SZPk0IiJjQnJXc3FxcmpKWW8">PDF</a>, pp.&nbsp;241-246).</p>
<p>Will it one day be possible to prevent deviations by treating perpetrators of violent acts early using this technique? Clinical trials may answer this question in the next two decades. In the meantime, it is important to remember that the visibility of laboratory studies is limited, as the most ‘violent’ experimental protocols use only small, low-intensity electric shocks with no consequences.</p>
</section>
<section id="syndrome-e-amphetamines-and-psychopathy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="syndrome-e-amphetamines-and-psychopathy">Syndrome E, Amphetamines, and Psychopathy</h2>
<p>Nearly 20 years ago, neuroscientist Itzhak Fried already suggested that individuals capable of killing coldly stand out less for dysfunctional reasoning than for a ‘cognitive fracture’ between emotional and decision-making processes [<a href="http://cnl.ucla.edu/Pubs/Fried%20The%20Lancet%20(1997).pdf">PDF</a>]. This fracture would lead to what Fried called ‘Syndrome E,’ related to <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psychopathie">psychopathy</a>, which combines a lack of empathy with various emotional changes.</p>
<p>Moreover, without profoundly altering free will or intent as some <a href="http://www.lesinrocks.com/2015/12/20/actualite/le-captagon-adjuvant-de-la-propagande-terroriste-11793573/">widespread fantasy</a> might suggest, cocaine and <a href="http://www.rfi.fr/moyen-orient/20151026-liban-prince-saoudien-arrete-beyrouth-apres-saisie-drogue-captagon-trafic">amphetamines used</a> by some jihadists can nevertheless facilitate the act and composure. Prior to the act itself, because they affect the <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dopamine">dopaminergic</a> system and <a href="https://www.researchgate.net/publication/235728208_Deficient_fear_recognition_in_regular_cocaine_users_is_not_attributable_to_elevated_impulsivity_or_conduct_disorder_prior_to_cocaine_use">alter</a> the activities of the amygdala, these psychostimulants somewhat mimic psychopathy and induce significant narcissism, excessive self-confidence, and heightened sensitivity to issues of social dominance. The encounter with these substances may therefore play a role in personality changes that precede or accompany radicalization.</p>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>In conclusion, we hope to have demonstrated that research into the causes of terrorism, at both the individual and social group levels, is feasible, desirable, and that its findings sometimes directly oppose certain preconceived ideas about the phenomenon. This is why the notion that the only brains that matter are those we have yet to kill or imprison is particularly deadly.</p>
<p>By focusing our attention on this elusive ‘brain behind the attacks’ that supposedly hops between the bombs of our Rafales, we lose sight of the essential: the causes that led some French people to sacrifice their lives to punish the people they are supposed to belong to. Just like the real-fake ‘closure of borders’ enacted and then canceled by François Hollande on the evening of November 13, or the absurd debate on ‘nationality revocation,’ the hunt for the ‘brain behind the attacks’ fits into a subtle game of semantic shifts that likely serve the electoral ambitions of some but also oppose intelligent counter-terrorism efforts.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.nouvelobs.com/rue89/rue89-neuro89/20160117.RUE2220/le-cerveau-des-attentats-au-pied-de-la-lettre.html"><strong>Link to the original article</strong></a></p>
<script src="https://giscus.app/client.js" data-repo="romainligneul/giscus-comments" data-repo-id="R_kgDOMSMTIw" data-category="CommentsBlogFR" data-category-id="DIC_kwDOMSMTI84CglZk" data-mapping="pathname" data-strict="0" data-reactions-enabled="1" data-emit-metadata="0" data-input-position="top" data-theme="preferred_color_scheme" data-lang="en" crossorigin="anonymous" async="">
</script>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>neuro89</category>
  <category>terrorism</category>
  <category>neuroscience</category>
  <category>conspiracy theories</category>
  <category>media</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/terroristbrain/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 16 Jan 2016 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/terroristbrain/dore_cerveau_attentats.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Conspiracy Theories: Why Does the Brain Get Tangled When It Gets Involved?</title>
  <dc:creator>RL, Neuro89</dc:creator>
  <link>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainconspiracy/</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 





<p>Because conspiracy theories address an increasingly inquisitive public in the face of a rapidly evolving history, articles aimed at demystifying these theories essentially answer the same question as the conspiracy sites themselves: what to believe and whom to trust?</p>
<section id="a-question-of-bad-faith" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="a-question-of-bad-faith">A Question of Bad Faith?</h2>
<p>Schematically, any conspiracy theory or anti-theory is rooted either in the desire to defend a specific interest or ideology, or in the intent to promote the “truth” about observed historical events. Thus, bad faith discourses oppose good faith discourses, in both camps, and the challenge is to consider the interests and ideologies defended by each side without reducing criticism to a series of ad hominem arguments that attribute credibility or discredit to different discourses solely based on the speaker.</p>
<p>It is not because an individual is an engineer at Monsanto, a government minister, a member of an anti-Zionist association, or a journalist at a major media outlet that their discourse should be taken as inherently true or false. It is the test of facts and adherence to logic that should constitute the standard of truth in this area as in any other.</p>
<p>Bad faith only begins when we continue to defend a false belief because it justifies our current or future actions. For example, imagine that in January 2016, French intelligence discovers that the November attacks were actually carried out by jihadists residing in Egypt, in retaliation for France’s military support to dictator al-Sisi, who is himself <a href="http://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Massacre_de_la_place_Rabia-El-Adaou%C3%AFa">responsible for the massacre at Rabia-El-Adawiya Square</a>. It is understandable that such a discovery would be difficult to communicate to the French public, as it would require justifying France’s position on Syrian and Egyptian issues differently. In this situation, what to do? The simplest solution might seem to be to maintain an official version of events while working behind the scenes to refocus the fight against our real enemies. But once such a divergence is created between official history and real history, how can we prevent citizens, journalists, and academics seeking understanding from pointing out inconsistencies and speculating on undisclosed information?</p>
</section>
<section id="pious-lies-of-the-state-and-democracy" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="pious-lies-of-the-state-and-democracy">Pious Lies of the State and Democracy</h2>
<p>The moral legitimacy of the pious lie is linked to a millennial philosophical question, to which this post does not need to take a side. We will only point out that, in this matter, the “deontological” approach defended by thinkers who aim for truth, such as <a href="http://la-philosophie.com/kant-mensonge">Kant</a> or <a href="http://ugo.bratelli.free.fr/Platon/Platon-HippiasMineur.htm">Plato</a>, contrasts with the “utilitarian” approach advocated by thinkers aiming for happiness, such as <a href="http://www.philolog.fr/y-a-t-il-des-mensonges-innocents/">Rousseau</a> or <a href="http://www.philagora.net/etude-de-texte/mill-texte-verite.php">Mill</a>.</p>
<p>Not all lies are pious, but believing that all lies are told with malicious intent is a sign of extreme and pathological conspiracism. Yes, we are likely lied to, but why assume that every lie necessarily reflects a malevolent intention towards the French people in general or a particular minority of French citizens? Let us guard against this type of conspiracism and assume that the lies that create a divergence between real history and official history stem from good intentions.</p>
<p>By definition, a pious lie submits the ideal of Truth to the quest for Good, and if we are subjected to such a lie, it means that individuals with access to the “truth” believe it to be contrary to the “good” of those without access to it, resulting in a double problem.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>On one hand, where does the idea come from that the public would be incapable of understanding and accepting the real reasons behind a political decision or a war?</p></li>
<li><p>On the other hand, where does this “good” pursued by those who lie so piously come from?</p></li>
</ul>
<p>In other words, the pious lie is based on the distinction between two social classes: one enlightened and informed, deciding for another, confused and misinformed. In fact, in this enlightening 2009 interview, François Hollande himself denounced the perverse logic of state lies told in the name of the fight against terrorism.</p>
<p>François Hollande in 2009, on the Sarkozy government’s handling of the terrorist issue</p>
<p>Furthermore, as beneficial as they might be for maintaining public order and the homeland as a whole, some pious lies can have detrimental consequences. In fact, it is often the plausibility of the lie and the skill with which it is executed that determine its adverse effects. Imagine a doctor trying to reassure a patient by hiding part of the test results. If the doctor lies poorly or if some of their pious lies have been discovered in the past, the patient, lacking confidence, might imagine suffering from a more serious illness than the one they actually have!</p>
<p>In the social and political realm, bad lies, when detected as such, can cause the public to fear the future and others more than if the truth were exposed by “those who know.” To take a recent example, it is difficult to believe in the fortuitous nature of the “suicide” of <a href="http://www.leparisien.fr/espace-premium/actu/deux-suicides-de-commissaire-en-deux-ans-09-01-2015-4430779.php">Commissioner Helric Fredou</a> on the very night of the Charlie Hebdo attacks. This case, on which the government only communicated in December, <a href="http://questions.assemblee-nationale.fr/q14/14-73052QE.htm">despite a request from a deputy in January</a>, has actively fueled various conspiracy theories. What might appear as a necessary pious lie has thus become the focal point of often fantastical and terrifying discourses about the supposed involvement of the government in this series of murders. One might even think that the truth about this somewhat mysterious death – however unsettling – would be far less worrying than the speculations induced by the government’s silence.</p>
<p>If we assume that some pious lies are useful and necessary for the exercise of power, should we then urge those who lie to “lie better,” as <a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rK32-i7YNy4">Didier Super humorously does in one of his recent videos</a>?</p>
<div class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainconspiracy/arretetonchar.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" width="482"></p>
<figcaption>A sign “Stop your nonsense: read” in tribute to the victims of the Charlie Hebdo attack, on the monument at Place de la République, January 11, 2015, Paris - JOEL SAGET/AFP</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>Unless we fall into a mystifying idealism that believes the government and media always know and relay the entire truth about the history unfolding before our eyes, the above considerations justify critical reflection, investigative journalism, and a generally skeptical position towards discourses from both the most dominant and the most protesting castes in our society. Nevertheless, why does this noble quest for truth so often take the form of a conspiracy theory and conspiracism, which involves attributing responsibility for significant events and the simultaneous construction of the official version to a small group of people organized in a secret society?</p>
<p>There are many possible answers to this question, but three main causes can be distinguished for the emergence of such theories.</p>
<ul>
<li><p>On one hand, conspiracies and plots have existed and still exist, so it can sometimes be justified to consider this hypothesis – with all the necessary precautions.</p></li>
<li><p>On the other hand, as a discourse, conspiracism can serve to defend specific interests or promote particular ideologies. For example, sites like Panamza or Égalité et Réconciliation clearly distinguish themselves by their anti-Zionism, so the systematic search for connections between the State of Israel and the attacks in France appears more as a business model than investigative journalism.</p></li>
<li><p>Finally, as explained very well (among other things) in <a href="http://agone.org/revueagone/agone47/enligne">the special issue of the Agone history journal</a> published in January 2012, the very term “conspiracy theory” is sometimes used to actively discredit certain non-conforming discourses and forms of investigative journalism.</p></li>
</ul>
<p>While we can understand why conspiracy theories emerge in public debate, these explanations do not tell us why they sometimes irrationally captivate their audience. This is where (neuro)sciences can help.</p>
</section>
<section id="theory-of-mind" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theory-of-mind">Theory of Mind</h2>
<p>As we have seen earlier, when the truth is obscured about important events, even if it is to facilitate governance oriented towards the public good, it can lead to a significant loss of trust in the official discourse, whether it comes directly from those who govern or the media that relay their statements. Thus, the citizen finds themselves in suspense and the field of “possible truths” expands: in addition to the difficulty of understanding already tremendously complex facts, there is added uncertainty about the facts themselves.</p>
<p>Now, what “cognitive tools” are available to humans confronted with such uncertainties? There are two main cognitive mechanisms that can be activated:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p><strong>To hold to previously acquired knowledge</strong>, since the human mind tends to prefer certainty. For instance, if a subject has previously believed that an attack was carried out by jihadists of Saudi origin, they are more likely to think that new and diverse information will fit within this preconceived framework.</p></li>
<li><p><strong>To try to attribute the observed facts to a coherent, internalized representation of a global truth</strong>, even if this representation is completely speculative or unverified. This cognitive tendency to seek an overall coherence has been extensively studied under the umbrella of the “theory of mind” in cognitive sciences.</p></li>
</ol>
<section id="theory-of-mind-the-role-of-agency-and-conspiracy" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="theory-of-mind-the-role-of-agency-and-conspiracy">Theory of Mind: The Role of Agency and Conspiracy</h3>
<p>The theory of mind involves the ability to attribute mental states (like beliefs, desires, and intentions) to oneself and others. This cognitive ability allows individuals to understand that others have thoughts and perspectives that differ from their own. It’s crucial for social interactions and understanding intentions behind actions.</p>
<p>When a significant event occurs, and there’s a lack of transparent information, people tend to employ their theory of mind to make sense of it. This often leads them to infer the presence of hidden agents or intentions behind the events. For instance, if an attack occurs and official explanations seem unsatisfactory, people might infer that a hidden group or agency is responsible, trying to fill in the gaps with their own theories.</p>
<p><strong>The Agency Detection Framework</strong> is one theoretical perspective that explains why people might believe in conspiracy theories. According to this framework, humans have evolved to detect agency – that is, to recognize when intentional actions are at play. This ability is essential for survival, helping humans avoid danger and understand the behavior of others. When faced with ambiguous or complex events, this innate tendency can lead people to attribute the events to malevolent agents or secretive groups, even when there is no concrete evidence.</p>
</section>
<section id="coherence-theory-making-sense-of-the-world" class="level3">
<h3 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="coherence-theory-making-sense-of-the-world">Coherence Theory: Making Sense of the World</h3>
<p>The coherence theory suggests that people strive to create a coherent narrative that makes sense of disparate pieces of information. When faced with incomplete or conflicting information, individuals attempt to construct a unified story that ties together the available facts. This drive for coherence can lead people to adopt conspiracy theories, as these theories often offer a seemingly comprehensive explanation that ties together various elements of an event in a way that makes sense within the theory’s framework.</p>
<p>In summary, the human brain’s tendency to detect agency and seek coherence plays a significant role in the formation and attraction of conspiracy theories. When faced with uncertain or incomplete information, people use these cognitive mechanisms to construct and cling to theories that provide a sense of understanding and predictability in an otherwise chaotic and opaque world.</p>
</section>
</section>
<section id="conclusion" class="level2">
<h2 class="anchored" data-anchor-id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Understanding the cognitive underpinnings of conspiracy theories helps us appreciate why they captivate and persist despite a lack of concrete evidence. By recognizing the role of theory of mind, agency detection, and coherence theory, we can better grasp why some people are drawn to these theories and how they function in the broader context of information processing and belief formation. This insight also highlights the importance of critical thinking and transparent communication in mitigating the spread and impact of conspiracy theories.</p>


</section>

 ]]></description>
  <category>neuro89</category>
  <category>terrorism</category>
  <category>cognitive sciences</category>
  <category>conspiracy theories</category>
  <guid>https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainconspiracy/</guid>
  <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2016 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://romainligneul.github.io/blog_en/posts/brainconspiracy/arretetonchar.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
